<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>None but Christ, or A sermon upon Acts 4. 12. Preached at St. Maries in Cambridge, on the commencement Sabbath, July 4. 1652. To which is annexed, an enquiry after what hope may be had of the salvation of [brace] 1. Heathens. 2. Those of the old world, the Jews and others before Christ. 3. Such as die infants, and idiots, &amp;c. now under the Gospel. / By Anthony Tuckney, D.D. and Master of St. Johns Colledge in Cambridge.</title>
            <author>Tuckney, Anthony, 1599-1670.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 191 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95352</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3217</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1523_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208588</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867529</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867529</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119845</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95352)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119845)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 194:E1523[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>None but Christ, or A sermon upon Acts 4. 12. Preached at St. Maries in Cambridge, on the commencement Sabbath, July 4. 1652. To which is annexed, an enquiry after what hope may be had of the salvation of [brace] 1. Heathens. 2. Those of the old world, the Jews and others before Christ. 3. Such as die infants, and idiots, &amp;c. now under the Gospel. / By Anthony Tuckney, D.D. and Master of St. Johns Colledge in Cambridge.</title>
                  <author>Tuckney, Anthony, 1599-1670.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>143, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Rothwell, and S. Gellibrand.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"1. Heathens. .. Gospel." are bracketed together on title page.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Acts VI, 12 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119845:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119845:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>None but Chriſt, OR A SERMON Upon <hi>Acts</hi> 4. 12. Preached at St. <hi>Maries</hi> in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> on the Commence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Sabbath, <hi>July</hi> 4. 1652. To which is annexed, an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry after what hope may be had Of the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of
<list>
                  <item>1. Heathens.</item>
                  <item>2. Thoſe of the old world, the <hi>Jews</hi> and others be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt.</item>
                  <item>3. Such as die Infants, and Idiots, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> now under the Goſpel.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Anthony Tuckney,</hi> D. D. and Maſter of St. <hi>Johns</hi> Colledge in <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Qui dicit hominem ſervari poſſe ſine Chriſto, Dubito an ipſe per Chriſtum ſervari poteſt Auguſtin.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Rothwell,</hi> and <hi>S. Gellibrand.</hi> 1654.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:119845:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:119845:2"/>
            <head>None but CHRIST.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>ACTS 4. 12.</bibl>
               <q>Neither is there ſalvation in any other: for there is none other name under Heaven given a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men, whereby we muſt be ſaved.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IN the beginning of the Chapter, we meet with the firſt perſecution of the Goſpel, recorded in Scripture, after our Saviours Aſcenſion. Sad,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119845:3"/> that ſo good news ſhould finde ſo bad entertainment! but happy for ſome, that as it was raiſed for ſo good a <hi>word,</hi> ſo occaſioned by ſo good a
<note place="margin">Mat. 13. 21</note> 
               <hi>deed</hi> done to an impotent man in the foregoing Chapter. Such may ever our ſufferings be, that if a black ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow muſt needs follow us, it may be only becauſe we walk in the light; and that if it prove our lot to heare and fare ill, it may be for <hi>doing well,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3. 17</note> and that the Apoſtle ſaith, is to <hi>ſuffer as a Chriſtian, 1 Pet.</hi> 4. 16. Nay, as <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf; for ſuch good works he was once to have been <hi>ſtoned. John</hi> 10. 32. and for the like, <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> were here arraigned and queſtioned, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <note place="margin">Verſe 7.</note> by what <hi>Name</hi> or <hi>Authority,</hi> or by what <hi>power</hi> or <hi>vertue. Qua arte Medica vel Magica</hi> (as it was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary to account both <hi>Chriſt</hi> and Chriſtians in the primitive times, to
<note place="margin">Grotius Lyranus.</note> be <hi>Conjurers)</hi> they had done <hi>This: The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ophylact</hi> and <hi>Oecumenius</hi> obſerve they were aſhamed to name it, being an high act of charity, and muſt it be made a matter of accuſation by their malice and envy? Curſed men! who accounting it a credit for them to do
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119845:3"/> 
               <hi>evill,</hi> make it a crime for the Apoſtles to do <hi>good; enviouſly malicious,</hi> that men may not act charity, without purchaſing their <hi>Licenſe ad practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candum:</hi> and <hi>withall, apparently ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous,</hi> in asking, <hi>by what power,</hi> when the thing it ſelf proclaimed it to be done by the power of God.</p>
            <p>And therefore, to this their <hi>fooliſh proud Queſtion,</hi> verſe 7. <hi>Peter</hi> returns <note place="margin">Matth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 69, 70.</note> a <hi>plain and round anſwer</hi> from <hi>verſe</hi> 8. to 13. And ſo He, who ſometimes full of himſelf, was baffled by a Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſel, now being filled with the <hi>holy Ghoſt,</hi> verſe 8. ſilenceth and confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth his not more potent then mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious accuſers and Judges, v. 13, 14. How woſully weak are we, when we rely on our own ſtrength; but how able to do all things, when <hi>Chriſt ſtrengtheneth us? In te ſtas &amp; non ſtas,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Phil. 4. 13.</note> ſaith <hi>Auſtin.</hi> Thou art ſure to come down, when thou ſtandeſt on thine <hi>own leggs;</hi> but how mightily upheld and carried on, when ſupported and conducted by <hi>Gods hand?</hi> As the Ship, which when the ſale is filled with a ſtrong gale, goeth on amaine; in a calm, notwithſtanding all our
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119845:4"/> rowing, is carried down the ſtream. And therefore when <hi>Moſes</hi> had pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for <hi>Judah,</hi> that his <hi>hands might be ſufficient for him,</hi> he added (as there was need.) <hi>And be thou an help to him, Deut. 33. 7. In hoc ſigno vinces. Go out in this thy ſtrength, and thou ſhalt prevail. Judg. 6. 14. Ithiel and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>cal</hi> here are Twins, the firſt of thoſe names ſaith, <hi>God is with me,</hi> and then <note place="margin">Prov. 30. 1.</note> the ſecond aſſureth me, that I ſhall be <hi>able to prevail,</hi> whatſoever, or who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is againſt me.</p>
            <p>If you look into the fifth and ſixth verſes, you ſhall ſee a very <hi>full Bench,</hi> not of <hi>Juſtices,</hi> but of <hi>profeſſed potent enemies:</hi> and this of <hi>all parties,</hi> who in other things could not agree; and from all <hi>parties,</hi> Its ſaid, they <hi>were gathered together,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>at or unto Jeruſalem,</hi> as though there had not been enow in the <hi>City,</hi> all were ſent for out of the Country, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>now, one would have thought, to have daſht a poor priſoner in <hi>bonds,</hi> and now at the <hi>Barre,</hi> quite out of countenance; But O the <hi>ingenuous boldneſse of</hi> a good <hi>conſcience in a good cauſe! Peter</hi> there makes an open Proclamation, with a <hi>Noverint <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſi.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119845:4"/> Be it known unto you all, that by the name of Jeſus Chriſt, doth this man ſtand before you whole.</hi> He dare beare witneſſe to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>againſt</hi> their ſin together, that as ſo many <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> they had <hi>rejected that ſtone which God had made the head of the corner,</hi> and as ſo many <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> had killed him, who had given to that poor man, health and life, verſ. 10, 11. yea, and ſalvation to all, in the Text. <hi>Neither is there ſalvation in any other, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which words we have</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>A confident Aſſertion.</hi> That there is no ſalvation, but by <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. As <hi>ſtrong a proof of it,</hi> taken from <hi>Gods</hi> deſignation, becauſe no <note place="margin">Explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the words.</note> 
               <hi>name under Heaven is given us, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we may be ſaved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Neither is there ſalvation. i. e.</hi> not ſo much as any <hi>temporal,</hi> much leſſe any <hi>ſpiritual</hi> and <hi>eternal</hi> ſalvation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In</hi> or by <hi>any other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For,</hi> here he gives a ſufficient rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Alius, vel alia vis cuju squam Sive auto ritas: Beza: Grotius. in</hi> 2 Tim. 2. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There is no name, i. e. Perſon,</hi> as <hi>Act</hi> 1. 1. 15. or <hi>Sec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> (which were wont to be called by the names of their <hi>Maſters,)</hi> or <hi>way,</hi> or <hi>Authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:119845:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder Heaven.</hi> Not as though we may hope for any other Saviours, (as Saints and Angels) <hi>in heaven;</hi> but to expreſſe the place where our ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was purchaſed, and that was here on earth <hi>under heaven,</hi> which the <hi>Socinian</hi> will have accompliſhed on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>in Heaven;</hi> but although the blood of the ſacrifice was preſented in the <hi>holy of holies,</hi> yet it was ſhed without <note place="margin">Levit. 16. 11, 12. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> to make an attonement: and ſo Chriſt our bleſſed High Prieſt, <hi>who for us men and our ſalvation</hi> came down from Heaven, returned indeed again to Heaven, and <hi>entred into the holy place with his</hi> own blood, <hi>yet it was</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 9. 12.</note> 
               <hi>having obtained eternal redemption for us,</hi> by that his blood ſhed here on earth; <hi>de coelo eſt ſalus, ſed ſub coelo</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lorinus.</note> 
               <hi>medium ſalutis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or (it may be) this expreſſion <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Heaven</hi> holdeth forth rather the extent of our Saviours Empire, and ſo <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is as much as <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſpiam.</hi> So <hi>Beza,</hi> and ſo <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. 12. We finde that phraſe <hi>under the whole Heaven,</hi> uſed in this ſenſe, in which <hi>no name under Heaven,</hi> here ſignifieth, <hi>None at all, or any where.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:119845:5"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Either the ſame with <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as we ſo finde the like phraſe, Chap. 7. 44. and ſo the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar here readeth it <hi>Hominibus, to men.</hi> Or as <hi>Ours</hi> render it, <hi>among men,</hi> who were very many, and had amongſt them many other conceited wayes of ſalvation, and many of them were very great <hi>Names</hi> in the world; and yet <hi>amongſt</hi> them All, <hi>no other name</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>given. i. e.</hi> by God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned, appointed, and that indeed of <hi>free gift.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>In</hi> or <hi>by which</hi> we <hi>muſt be ſaved.</hi> Not as though there were any neceſſity in regard of us, or our worth, that therefore we muſt needs be ſaved; but to expreſſe thus much, that if through <hi>Gods</hi> free grace we be ſaved, it then neceſſarily <hi>muſt</hi> be only in and by <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> which is the <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctrine</hi> of the <hi>Text,</hi> and which we are now to inſiſt on.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Beſides, or without Chriſt no ſalvation:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt</hi> ſaith, <note place="margin">Doct. Evange<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Jeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſti non eſt Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelium <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum. Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. wright.</note> 
               <hi>Mark</hi> Chap. 1. 1. It is ſo in his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, that there is no ſuch good news, but by him, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>The Chriſt, The Saviour.</hi> John 4. 42. ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken not only <hi>emphatically,</hi> but alſo
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119845:6"/> 
               <hi>excluſively. The Chriſt</hi> is ſo <hi>the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour,</hi> that he is <hi>the only Saviour.</hi> But your Chriſtian belief will not need the proof of this <hi>fundamental ſum of the Doctrine of Chriſt.</hi> It would be hard to be put upon the proof of firſt <hi>Principles,</hi> and ſometimes proves hard, when unreaſonably put upon it, to do it, which would be but the emblaſoning of a ſun-beam, or the laying on a colour to make Ivory or Snow the whiter: A man hath never leſſe to ſay, than when, that which he is to prove or cleare, is more certain and manifeſt than his proof; <hi>omni <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uce</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mornay. de veritat. Cap.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>clarius, omni interpretatione notius.</hi> Such hard tasks are we now put upon in theſe our ſinful dayes, which at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to raſe the moſt grounded <hi>Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentalls</hi> of Religion; but bleſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d be <hi>GOD,</hi> that there is leſſe difficulty in proving this, which is of ſuch ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute neceſſity to ſalvation, That out of <hi>Chriſt</hi> there is no ſalvation. <hi>Haec Petri ſententia,</hi> (as he ſaith) <hi>eſt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Sarcerius.</note> 
               <hi>Decretum ſuper omnium conciliorum decreta,</hi> not to be doubtfully diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but yet may be fully proved. <note place="margin">Pſal. 118. 22. Iſa. 28. 16. Eph. 2. 20.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. From the <hi>Titles</hi> given to <hi>Chriſt</hi> in Scripture, as <hi>The corner ſtone</hi> and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119845:6"/> 
               <hi>Foundation.</hi> So that if, either it be laid aſide (as in the verſe before the Text) or we be not laid upon it, we build upon the ſand, and utterly ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine all, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7. 26, 27. The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> is peremptory, that <hi>no man can lay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3. 11.</note> 
               <hi>other foundation,</hi> and therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides him no ſalvation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Root</hi> and <hi>true Vine.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note place="margin">Coloſ. 2. 7.</note> if not implanted and rooted in him, we ſhall certainly wither, and become fewel for <hi>everlaſting burnings.</hi> John 15. 1. to 9.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The head of the body.</hi> And then, <note place="margin">C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 18.</note> though <hi>Popiſh Legends</hi> can tell you of men walking without their heads, yet ſober Chriſtians are no <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Hereticks.</hi> The ſtrength of the ſheep of <hi>Chriſts</hi> paſture is in their Head, and all their life and vigour from u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with it, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 16. ſo that the body may as well live without the head, as we without <hi>Chriſt</hi> gain ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The beloved-Husband,</hi> by whom a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone the chaſt <hi>ſpouſe</hi> bringeth forth
<note place="margin">2 Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 2.</note> fruit unto God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 4. and ſhe is but an Harlot that embraceth the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom of a ſtranger.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Mediator</hi> and the only one, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119845:7"/> as God himſelf is one, <hi>one God, and one Mediator between God and Man, and that only the man Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.</hi> 1 Tim. 2. 5. A proof which St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> very often and ſtrongly urgeth <note place="margin">Contra Julian.</note> to this purpoſe. It is no <hi>Platonick faith</hi> (as ſome call it) which can u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite us at ſo great an odds to <hi>God,</hi> without <hi>Chriſt,</hi> our alone <hi>Mediator,</hi> to come between, and make up the breach, there will for ever remain <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an infinite diſtance, and immortal emnity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Door,</hi> which a blinde <hi>Sodomite</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Joh. 10. 9 Revel. 22. 15.</note> cannot finde, and therefore <hi>remains without with Dogs.</hi> Beſides which no entrance, either into the <hi>Church</hi> here, or <hi>Heaven</hi> hereafter.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, <hi>The way, the truth, and the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Joh. 14. 6.</note> 
               <hi>life.</hi> The true way to life, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>via illa certiſſima, qu â un â, &amp;c.</hi> As <hi>Beza</hi> upon the place, the only way, by which we may certainly, and out of which it is impoſſible we ſhould ever come to life, or the <hi>God</hi> of our life, as our <hi>Saviour</hi> addeth in the very next word, <hi>none commeth to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 17. 3.</note> 
               <hi>but by me.</hi> As elſewhere, <hi>This is eternal life to know thee and Jeſus Chriſt, whom thou haſt ſent,</hi> who is ſo
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119845:7"/> 
               <hi>the way, the truth, and the life,</hi> that out of him, we ſhall <hi>periſh from the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 2. 12.</note> 
               <hi>way;</hi> ſhall deceive our ſelves with a <hi>lye,</hi> if we believe not in this <hi>truth;</hi> and abide for ever in <hi>death,</hi> if not made partakers of this <hi>life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. This truth, that <hi>out of Chriſt no ſalvation</hi> is further made out from all the parts of this ſalvation, in the whole progreſs from firſt to laſt, all is <hi>in</hi> and <hi>by</hi> Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Elected in him, Epheſ.</hi> 1. 4.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Redeemed by him; in whom we have Redemption through his blood.</hi> verſe 7.</p>
            <p>If <hi>Adopted.</hi> It is in ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Elder Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> right, <hi>unto the Adoption of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren by Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> v. 5.</p>
            <p>If <hi>juſtified.</hi> It is by his <hi>righteouſneſs</hi> imputed; <hi>accepted,</hi> but <hi>in the Beloved.</hi> v. 6.</p>
            <p>If <hi>ſanctified.</hi> It is by his <hi>ſpirit</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated, <hi>He hath choſen us in him to be holy.</hi> v. 4.</p>
            <p>If <hi>ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed.</hi> It is by his <hi>merit</hi> impart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. <hi>In whom alſo we have obtained an Inheritance.</hi> v. 11.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And bleſſed with all ſpiritual bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings in heavenly places,</hi> but ſtill in <hi>Chriſt.</hi> v. 3.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:119845:8"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:119845:8"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:119845:9"/>
            <p>It is the groſſeſt <hi>darkneſs of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,</hi> that we <hi>lie in,</hi> unleſs he be our <hi>light and Prophet,</hi> to inlighten and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct us. <hi>Mat.</hi> 4. 16.</p>
            <p>It is the heavieſt <hi>guilt</hi> that we <hi>lie under,</hi> unleſſe he be our <hi>Prieſt,</hi> to make expiation for us, be our <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, 1 <hi>John 2. 2. Rom.</hi> 3. 25.</p>
            <p>And when that is done, a thouſand miſcarriages and miſchiefs from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and (ſhould all elſe fail) from our ſelves, would betide us, unleſs he be <hi>Melchizedeck King of Salem;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 7. 1.</note> Our King to govern and defend us, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9. 6. &amp; 33. 22.</p>
            <p>It is he only, <hi>who of God is made unto us, wiſdom, righteouſneſſe, ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication and redemption, 1 Cor. 1. 30. even all in all. Col.</hi> 3. 11. And then if he be <hi>All, All</hi> beſides him are <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</hi> And ſo ſtill without him, no one part of ſalvation.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And this is true of all <hi>perſons in all places,</hi> as he is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſo <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>All,</hi> and this <hi>unto All, Col.</hi> 3. 11. The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> there makes a large enumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Greek, Jew; circumciſion, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſion; Barbarian, Scythian; Bond, free;</hi> He was as <hi>well a light to the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119845:9"/> Gentiles, as the glory of his people Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke 2. 32</note> From <hi>Eaſt</hi> to <hi>Weſt,</hi> this <hi>Sun of righteouſneſſe</hi> enlightens all, And if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny without the <hi>Tropick</hi> of the more <hi>viſible Church</hi> ſhould have the <hi>light of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">John 8. 12</note> 
               <hi>life,</hi> it is from more oblique beams, which by wayes beſt known to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, he dart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th upon them where ever they be, if they be <hi>under the whole Heaven,</hi> or <hi>amongſt men:</hi> the Text tells them to whom they muſt be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden for ſalvation. Of which if <hi>we</hi> yet doubt, <hi>Auſtin,</hi> I am ſure, is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain. <hi>Certus ſum non eſſe animam ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Epiſt. 28.</note> 
               <hi>in genere humano, cui non ſit neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarius ad liberationem Mediator Dei &amp; hominum, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. And thus, laſtly, in reference to all <hi>Times</hi> and <hi>Ages,</hi> whether of <hi>our life,</hi> or of the <hi>world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Of our life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we be grown up to be <hi>men,</hi> it will be more eaſily granted, <hi>that he that believeth not ſhall be damned,</hi> Mark 16. 16.</p>
            <p>And for thoſe that die <hi>Infants,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we cannot ſo eaſily under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand how they ſhould actually be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, yet we muſt believe, that <hi>unleſſe unto us a Child were born, and a Son
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119845:10"/> given,</hi> they, who in themſelves are <hi>Children of wrath,</hi> would never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>heyrs of life.</hi> This alſo is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Article</hi> of <hi>Auſtins</hi> Creed, which <note place="margin">Epiſt. 157.</note> he would have kept inviolate. <hi>Illa fides in nobis ſalva ſit, quâ credimus, nullum hominem ſive majoris ſive par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulae, quamlibet &amp; recentioris aetatis liberari e contagione mortis aeternae, et obligatione peccati quam contraxit pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma ſua nativitate, niſi per unum Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atorem Dei et hominum, Jeſum Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum.</hi> Whether <hi>old or young,</hi> we muſt have the <hi>everlaſting Father</hi> to be <hi>the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſu. 9. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Prince of our peace,</hi> or elſe our breach is irreconcileable.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And the like is to be ſaid of the ſeveral <hi>Ages of the world,</hi> from firſt to laſt. Chriſt is the <hi>firſt and laſt,</hi> which <note place="margin">Rev. 1. 11. Epiſt. 157.</note> made St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſtill confidently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm in reference to this my Text. <hi>Ex <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o tempore valet ad ſervandum genus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">John 1. 29. Rev. 13. 8.</note> 
               <hi>humanum; ex quo in Adam eſt vitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, &amp;c.</hi> Chriſt the Lamb of God, that taketh <hi>away the ſins of the world,</hi> was ſlain <hi>from the beginning of the world.</hi> Which beleevers in all their ſacrifices (almoſt as ancient as the world) <note place="margin">De Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrat.</note> looked after, as <hi>Euſebius</hi> ſheweth, which made <hi>Ignatius</hi> conclude, that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119845:10"/> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note place="margin">Lib. 1. cap. 10. <hi>Ad Magneſ.</hi> Hiſtor. lib. 1. cap. 4.</note> and <hi>Euſebius</hi> in another place, to the ſame purpoſe calleth them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Chriſtians indeed, though not then ſo named, for in the faith of a <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> a <hi>Chriſt</hi> to come, they lived and died, and ſo were ſaved, as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth at large, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. So that as the whole body is under the <hi>Head,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">It a omnes ſancti qui ante Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni noſtri, <hi>J. C.</hi> nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitatem e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, quam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis ante nati erant, tamen cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pori uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſo ſed capiti cohae ſerunt. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin. Gregor. homil. 17. in Ezek.</note> though one part of it be born after another. So here alſo in this myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal body of Chriſt. As <hi>Auſtin</hi> compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth it; or as <hi>Gregory</hi> alluding to that paſſage of the Goſpel, expreſſeth it, Some went before, and ſome came after; but both, all, cry <hi>Hoſannah,</hi> (and that word ſignifieth ſalvation) <hi>to the Son of David.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a word, to conclude this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall proof, it is <hi>Pauls</hi> full ſcope in his moſt divine Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi> to prove that neither <hi>Jew</hi> nor <hi>Gentile</hi> can be juſtified or ſaved, but only by the faith of Chriſt, the <hi>ſecond Adam,</hi> by whom are ſaved all that are ſaved, as all were undone by the firſt. But ſhould I recite all Scripture-proofs of this truth, I ſhould tranſcribe the greateſt part of the <hi>old and new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119845:11"/> Bernard</hi> ſaith of ſome, that by <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dum mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ſudat quo modo Platonem faciat Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianum, ſe probat Ethnicum, Epiſt.</hi> 190.</note> labouring to prove <hi>Plato</hi> to be a <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian,</hi> proved themſelves no <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> which makes me fear I ſhould too much wrong both my ſelf, and this moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Auditory, as though it were ſcarce <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> if I ſhould labour too long in the proof of this <hi>fundamental</hi> &amp; characteriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Article of their <hi>Chriſtianity;</hi> And therefore I the rather come to the ground of it in the</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> Second part of the Text. There is <hi>ſalvation in none other,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>there is no other name gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, whereby we muſt be ſaved.</hi> And it is taken (as <hi>Calvin</hi> obſerveth, from <note place="margin">Explicatio eſt proximae ſententiae, in Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſolo eſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, quo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am it a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us decrevit &amp;c. Calvin in locum.</note> 
               <hi>Gods free purpoſe,</hi> which is eſpecially to be heeded in matters of his <hi>free grace,</hi> and if he appointed no other, then it is high preſumption in us to fanſie any other. When in our ſelves we are all juſtly condemned, we muſt give <hi>God</hi> leave to chuſe, as whom he will ſave, ſo by what means he will procure and diſpenſe this ſalvation. And if for that he hath made choyce only of Chriſt, as in ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects <hi>neceſſary,</hi> but in all reſpects, as
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:119845:11"/> 
               <hi>Auſtin truly ſaith, abſolutely moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>andae noſtraemiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae, conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nientiorem modum non fuiſſe. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt. de Tem. lib. 13 Cap. 10 aliter abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutè potuit ſalvaſſe mundum, licet ad ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem de rigore juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae videtur neceſſari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> hypoſtatica unio Lori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus. Orthodox. Eplicat.</hi> Lib. 3.</note> then he was not more blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous who ſaid he could have told <hi>God</hi> a better way to have made the world, then they are preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, who dare be ſo bold as in their wanton fancies to conceit another way of redeeming the world then by Chriſt alone, which was the moſt happy product of the moſt divine Counſels of all the three <hi>Perſons</hi> in the bleſſed <hi>Trinity</hi> from all eternity. And ſhall we then attempt to be wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer than <hi>God,</hi> and in effect ſay, that <hi>He</hi> might have ſpared his Counſels, and <hi>Chriſt</hi> his death, Seeing there may be a way for ſuch as never knew him, to come to life without him? ſo <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dradius</hi> ſticks not to accuſe God for cruelty, if it ſhould be otherwiſe. But when the Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſtion in the Prophet was, <hi>is there any other God beſides me?</hi> God thought he had ſufficiently an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered in the Negative, when he ſaid, <hi>I know none,</hi> Iſa. 44. 8. and ſo if the like queſtion be made of a <hi>Saviour,</hi> whether there be any other beſides <hi>Chriſt?</hi> let us ſit down ſatisfied with this, it is he only <hi>who of</hi> God <hi>is made</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 30.</note> 
               <hi>to us wiſdom, righteouſneſſe, &amp;c.</hi> He it
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119845:12"/> is <hi>whom the Father hath ſealed,</hi> and let <note place="margin">John 6. 27</note> that make this impreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on our hearts that although <hi>there be many that are</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 8. 5. 6.</note> 
               <hi>called Gods, &amp; Lords many,</hi> and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly, many conceited wayes of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and thereby of ſalvation; yet to us, as there was but one God, ſo <hi>but one Mediator between</hi> God <hi>and man, the man Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2. 5</note> let us have a <hi>Saviour</hi> of Gods chuſing and making, and not of our own framing and fanſying; for how miſerable ſhould I be, if whilſt I have been looking out for other wayes to ſave me, God who hath appointed this way, which I have neglected or miſſed of, ſhould damne me? It is my ſecurity, if when I can ſay, I have a <hi>manifeſt token of ſalvation,</hi> I can adde <note place="margin">Phil. 1. 28.</note> with the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>and this of God,</hi> becauſe in and by <note place="margin">Act 5. 31.</note> Chriſt, whom he hath appointed, and <hi>exalted to be Prince and Saviour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> To this adde in the ſecond place, <hi>that ſalvation is diſpenſed to us by way of Covenant:</hi> and had it been by the firſt Covenant of which the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> was head, his name might have been written on it; but ſeeing it is by the ſecond, of which <hi>Chriſt the ſecond A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:119845:12"/> is the only Head (as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſheweth in that divine parallel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the two <hi>Adams,</hi> Rom. 5) as he is made our <hi>Covenant,</hi> ſo alſo our ſalvation, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49. 6, 8. guilty we were and condemned by the <hi>firſt Adam,</hi> and therefore juſtified and ſaved we <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Concil. Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. de ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtific.</hi> Cap. 3.</note> muſt be by the <hi>ſecond,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. This <hi>opportet</hi> in the Text, is now not only of <hi>conveniency,</hi> but alſo of <hi>neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Nemo ad mortem niſi per illum, nemo ad vitam niſi per iſtum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> To this purpoſe conſider further, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is ſo the head of this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Covenant, that <hi>Gods</hi> glory in this exaltation is the chiefe end intended in it. In which Chriſt is not brought in <hi>per ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidens,</hi> or in an inferior ſubordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as a ſubſervient means to us and our ſalvation as the end, (though e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſo there would be no ſalvation without him, as no attaining the end, without the means, &amp; if there be but one only means to the end, it is as neceſſary as the end.) But <hi>Chriſts</hi> and <hi>Gods</hi> glory in him is the prime de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of it, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1. 6. That our ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion wrought by him ſhould be as a ſubordinate means to his glory, as
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119845:13"/> the chief end. And therefore as on the one ſide, we ſhould not ſo much look at <hi>Chriſt</hi> for our ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as at our ſalvation for Chriſt and his glory; ſo on the other ſide, if whilſt we take in <hi>ſalvation</hi> we leave out <hi>Chriſt,</hi> we cut off the ſtream from the fountain from which it floweth, and ſo our ſalvation would be an empty dry pit, prove vain, and fall ſhort of its end, and we of the comfort of it, if (whilſt we are ſaved ſome other way) he ſhould not have the honour of being (as he moſt certainly is) the <hi>Authour</hi> of <note place="margin">Heb. 5. 9.</note> it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>4</label> And as our ſalvation would ſo be empty and vain, ſo alſo our <hi>Saviour</hi> alſo ſhould have ſuffered and died in vain. It is <hi>Auſtins</hi> inference, <hi>gratis e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Contra Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lianum.</hi> Lib. 4. Cap. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſtus mortuus eſt, ſi homines ulli abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Chriſto ad fidem veram, virtutem veram, &amp;c. quacun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> re alia, quacun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> freti ratione perveniant:</hi> and <hi>Paul's</hi> before him, Gal. 2. 21. <hi>if righteouſneſſe come by the Law,</hi> (and ſo it muſt if not by Chriſt) <hi>then Chriſt is dead in vain.</hi> If any without him may now come to life, then <hi>ad quid perditio</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lib. 3. Cap. 47.</note> 
               <hi>haec?</hi> to <hi>what purpoſe was all that
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119845:13"/> waſt?</hi> was he ſo prodigal of his blood, that when (according to this opinion) we might have been ſaved, and that (as <hi>Bradwardine</hi> ſheweth) by an eaſier and readier way, without it? A damnable error! and fully confuted</p>
            <p>By the deare <hi>experience of every humbled ſinner,</hi> which fully convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth him of an abſolute neceſſity of having Chriſt, and of his moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain &amp; inevitable periſhing without him. As on the contrary, it is obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable, that they who are moſt for the other opinion, and ſo can lick them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and others whole, are leaſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with what a <hi>wounded con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> meaneth, and the work of <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-humiliation.</hi> Who, did they more know themſelves, would thereby come more to know the neceſſity of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and that ſuch a <hi>Demoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ack</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 17. 17</note> cannot be cured without being brought to him. As the <hi>Scripture</hi> all over proclaimeth that it was this our good <hi>Samaritan</hi> only, that pittied, when all elſe paſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d by, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took the cure, when all elſe had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven it over as d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſperate, even when <hi>there was none to help,</hi> then at ſuch a
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:119845:14"/> dead lift, and caſe of ſuch extream neceſſity, his <hi>arm only brought ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> Iſa. 63. 3, 5. And yet rather then a <hi>Philoſopher</hi> ſhould not be dubbd a <hi>Saint,</hi> and his <hi>moral vertues</hi> prov <hi>ſaving graces,</hi> and we have nothing inherent in our ſelves to ſtick to; <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted righteouſneſse</hi> not only by <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts</hi> muſt be derided; But be too much ſleighted and undervalued by too many amongſt our ſelves; the great <hi>myſtery of godlineſſe,</hi> and the whole counſel of God in Chriſt muſt all at once be daſht, and all the links of that <hi>golden Chain</hi> ſnapt aſunder, <hi>piè ſcilicet!</hi> And a fair requital it is, that we ſo make of Chriſts kindneſſe, when in effect we tell him, he might have kept it to himſelf, and we have fared never the worſe, ſeeing ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny have been, and all might have bin
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 17.</note> ſaved without him. I ſay, Chriſt ſhould ſo have died in vain.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>5</label> And then alſo our <hi>faith muſt needs be in vain,</hi> if Chriſt were not neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, our faith would be needleſſe;
<note place="margin">Strom. l. 1.</note> which yet <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> (much forgetting what elſewhere he ſaith of the <hi>Gentile,</hi> being juſtified by <hi>Philoſophy)</hi> calleth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119845:14"/> I am ſure the Scripture requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth it as the neceſſary <hi>Inſtrument</hi> of <hi>juſtification.</hi> Rom. 5. 1. and <hi>inlet to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,</hi> Epheſ. 2. 8. and that not onely <hi>neceſſitate praecepti,</hi> but <hi>Medii,</hi> as <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentia</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Tom. 3. diſt. 1. qu. 2. p. 317.</note> concludes, and as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> plainly ſheweth in that divine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion. <hi>Rom. 10. 13, 14. whoſoever ſhall call on the name of the Lord ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; but how ſhall they call on him, on whom they have not beleeved? and how ſhall they believe on him, of whom they have not heard?</hi> and accordingly, we read, <hi>Acts</hi> 11. 17, 18. that upon their beleeving by <hi>Peters</hi> preaching, the Diſciples inferred, that <hi>Then</hi> (and not till <hi>then) God had alſo to the Gentiles granted repentance unto life:</hi> as alſo chap. 15. 9. Then it was that he put no <hi>difference between Jew and Gentile, when once he had purified their hearts by faith.</hi> Thus we ſee, that faith is neceſſary, and that the <hi>word of faith, Rom.</hi> 10. 8. is <hi>the word of life. Phil.</hi> 2. 16. But what need of either becoming <hi>Proſelytes,</hi> under the Law or of ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out Apoſtles for the Miniſtry of the Goſpel, to them who had enough at home, to inſtruct them in the wayes of eternal life?</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:119845:15"/>
            <p>What neceſſity of reading the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> if the ſame leſſon may be taken out of the Book of the <hi>Creature?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or of hearing the <hi>Sermons</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> when Sun, Moon, and Stars were ſufficient <hi>preachers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo by this means, with this faith of Chriſt, if not all <hi>Religion,</hi> yet all <hi>Chriſtian Religion</hi> is gone too.</p>
            <p>Two things are here ſaid: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zuinglius de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>peccat: orig.</hi> Tom. 2. pag. 118.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That faith is required only where the Goſpel is preached. <hi>Mark</hi> 16. 15, 16. but as for them who never heard of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and ſo are invincibly ignorant of him, They hope their <hi>Negative Infidelity</hi> ſhall not damn them.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, not as an <hi>Operative cauſe,</hi> and containing new guilt, if the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance be really and totally <hi>invinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble;</hi> But yet as (if I may ſo call it) a <hi>defective Cauſe</hi> it will, they thereby falling ſhort of the only means to take away the old guilt, and ſo the man indeed dyeth of his old wounds; but withall, he neceſſarily dyeth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath not the Medicine which only could have cured him. And the <hi>Traytor</hi> is executed <hi>meritoriouſly</hi> for
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119845:15"/> his <hi>Treaſon;</hi> but unavoidably, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he wanteth his pardon, either not accepted, or not ſo much as heard of, which only ſhould, and could have ſaved him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But ſecondly they will grant, that indeed, <hi>without faith it is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to pleaſe God,</hi> and they muſt grant it, becauſe the Scripture expreſly ſaith it, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 6. but then they will tell you, that ſuch a faith will ſerve the turn, as the Apoſtle here ſpeaks of, <hi>viz.</hi> ſuch as believeth <hi>that God is, and that he is a rewarder of them that diligently ſeek him,</hi> as it is there de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, and ſuch a faith the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and ſuch as never heard of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> may have, and ſo pleaſe <hi>God,</hi> and be ſaved by it. This <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Nature's Champions,</hi> and the <hi>Heathens Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates</hi> apply to their wound, that it may not prove mortal, which they diſtinguiſh of an <hi>explicite</hi> and <hi>impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite</hi> faith; they conclude, that an <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicite</hi> faith may be ſufficient, and ſuch the Heathens might have, and had.</p>
            <p>For when they believed that there was a <hi>God, eandem habuerunt fidem in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119845:16"/> unius Dei credulitate incluſam.</hi> So <hi>Sixtus Senenſis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And when they believed <hi>that he was a Rewarder of thoſe that ſeek him,</hi> they did believe <hi>Gods</hi> providence, <hi>et per conſequens modum ſalutis humanae, ſaltem implicitum,</hi> and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, at leaſt implicitly the way and manner of mans ſalvation. So <note place="margin">Orthodox: Explic. pag. 292. quàm latè pateat Dei provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentia, &amp; quanta c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m vigilantia provideat rebus hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manis, ſatis intelliget humani ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neris per Chriſtum redemptio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vina provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentia im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitè &amp; abſconditè contineri.</note> 
               <hi>Rike<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which <hi>Andradius</hi> addeth, that he who ſhall conſider how farre <hi>Gods</hi> providence reacheth, and how watchfully it intendeth mans con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernments, he cannot but underſtand that the Redemption of man by <hi>Chriſt</hi> is implicitly contained in it.</p>
            <p>And <hi>ſome</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Mr. <hi>J. G.</hi> in his Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles debt and dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</note> 
               <hi>of late</hi> have told us, that whilſt <hi>they ſee heaven and earth,</hi> and <hi>the frame of nature continue, they may by Gods patience gather, that his wrath is pacified, and ſo come to the knowledge of a Mediator.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To all which I ſay</p>
            <p n="1">1. And firſt grant, that the like ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicit faith which is required of ſome, is not alike neceſſary to all for their ſalvation. For</p>
            <p>What is now <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> with <hi>open fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> revealed to us in the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:119845:16"/> times of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> was under the <note place="margin">2 Cor. 3. 18.</note> 
               <hi>Law</hi> vailed over with ſhadowes and Ceremonies, even to the godly then, who yet through them, looked at a Meſſiah for their ſalvation.</p>
            <p>Nor is it now prejudicial to weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er <hi>Chriſtians</hi> (as to their ſalvation) that they cannot ſo clearly and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly underſtand all the particulars in the ſeveral <hi>Articles</hi> of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an faith, as ſome do, who are more learned and able. The dim-ſighted man may certainly ſee his friend ſtanding by him, though not ſo clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as he who hath a quicker eye; and I may as truly ſee him ſtanding in the ſhade, though not ſo diſtinctly, as if he were in the Sun-ſhine.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But as the <hi>Popiſh implicite faith</hi> hath been a ſnare and ruine to many <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> ſo this farre-fetched, and fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re more <hi>implicated</hi> faith will at laſt be found inſufficient for the ſalvation of <hi>Heathens,</hi> and to evade the <hi>Apoſtles Sorites, viz.</hi> They that have not heard of a Saviour, do not, cannot believe <note place="margin">Rom. 10. 13, 14, 15.</note> in him; They that believe not in him, cannot call upon God; they that call not upon God, cannot be ſaved; and therefore <hi>a primo ad
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:119845:17"/> ultimum,</hi> they that have not heard of a Saviour cannot be ſaved.
<note place="margin">Lib. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orol. 132</note>
            </p>
            <p>I need not here inſiſt on what <hi>Brad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardine</hi> and other <hi>Schoolmen</hi> diſpute for the neceſſity of an <hi>explicite faith.</hi> This I am ſure of, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf ſaith, that <hi>this is eternal life, not only to know the Father to be the only true God, but alſo Jeſus Chriſt whom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e hath ſent,</hi> John 17. 3. and therefore would not have his <hi>Diſciples</hi> reſt in <hi>their beleeving in God, but would alſo have them believe in him.</hi> John 14. 1. And therefore.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For that in <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 6. of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving that <hi>God is, and that he is a rewarder:</hi> however (as <hi>Hugo</hi> obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) before the <hi>fall,</hi> faith in God as a
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>De ſacram:</hi> Lib. 1. Part. 10. Cap. 5. Iſa. 45. 22.</note> 
               <hi>Creator</hi> was ſufficient, yet not ſince, but we muſt of neceſſity look at him in a <hi>Redeemer,</hi> if we would (as the Prophet biddeth us) ſo look at him, <hi>as to be ſaved</hi> by him.</p>
            <p>And although a Chriſtian Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leever muſt by his juſtifying and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving faith, <hi>tanquam ex praeſuppoſito</hi> believe that God is, and that he is a righteous Judge, (which is all that
<note place="margin">Sentent. Lib. 3. diſt. 25.</note> can neceſſarily be inferred from that place) yet <hi>Lambard</hi> rightly addeth
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:119845:17"/> 
               <hi>non ſufficit.</hi> It is not all, not ſufficient and enough, either ſavingly to pleaſe him (elſe the Devils ſhould) or to make us <hi>come to him, and diligently to ſeek him;</hi> for then many deſperate and deſpairing ſinners ſhould, who yet, (even upon thought and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction of it) run away from him. And ſo we finde that the faith of all thoſe many beleevers, which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle in that ſame Chapter inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth in, went further: which plainly evinceth, that it is not a <hi>Philoſophical,</hi> but a <hi>Thelogical,</hi> not a <hi>natural</hi> but a <hi>ſupernatural</hi> knowledge that he there
<note place="margin">G. Valenti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> M. Canus.</note> ſpeaketh of. A belief that <hi>God is,</hi> but a <hi>God in Chriſt,</hi> and that <hi>he is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warder,</hi> but in an <hi>evangelical way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. And therefore for <hi>S. Senenſis</hi> his <hi>in unius Dei credulitate,</hi> &amp;c. that in the belief of <hi>one God,</hi> the faith of <hi>Chriſt God-man</hi> ſhould be contained ſufficiently to ſalvation. It will bring in a <hi>Saviour</hi> before the <hi>Fall,</hi> and finde him in the <hi>Covenant</hi> of <hi>works,</hi> as well as in the <hi>Covenant of grace,</hi> and make the <hi>Turk</hi> the true <hi>Muſulman</hi> (as he calls himſelf) as true a beleever as the beſt Chriſtian.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And for <hi>Andradius</hi> his conceit,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:119845:18"/> that the belief of Gods Providence, and how vigilant it is in the behalf of man <hi>in general,</hi> ſhould imply and contain the knowledge and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of this <hi>particular</hi> Providence of his ſaving man by a <hi>Meſſiah.</hi> It will take in all the men that have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver been in the world, except ſome few <hi>Atheiſts</hi> and <hi>Epicureans,</hi> that denyed a <hi>Deity</hi> and a <hi>Providence:</hi> nor it may be would they be excepted, if they had been rightly underſtood and reported of, who perhaps were taken to deny a <hi>Deity,</hi> when they only denied the falſe Deities which were then adored by others, and ſo poſſibly were leſſe Atheiſts than many then were, and now are: and ſo by this means, <hi>quae coelo ducit ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mita facta via eſt, the way and gate to Heaven,</hi> which our <hi>Saviour</hi> ſaith, <hi>is narrow, and ſtrait, and which</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 7. 14.</note> 
               <hi>few finde,</hi> will bee made farre wider then either they or any will finde it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And for what was ſaid, that by <hi>Gods</hi> patience in continuing the world, they may infer that hee is pacified; I onely ſay two things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, if they might poſſibly from
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:119845:18"/> thence infer a Mediatour, yet for all that they would be ſtill to ſeek who that Mediatour ſhould be, and ſo they would only erect an <hi>Altar to an</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 17. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3</note> 
               <hi>unknown God,</hi> but mean while have no knowledge or thought, that this <hi>Mediatour</hi> is <hi>Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> but the <hi>Jewes</hi> may think it is their long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looked-for <hi>Meſsiah,</hi> and the Turk may put in for his <hi>Mahomet,</hi> both which, and their ſalvation by either will come together. And if the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then</hi> ſtay till they both get in, he may come to be kept out for ever.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I adde that although a true believer by light <hi>from the word</hi> may from Gods patience inferre <hi>Chriſts mediation;</hi> yet others from theſe mens principles cannot neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily conclude ſo much, but onely might inferre that <hi>God</hi> is gracious and merciful, and ſo without the intervention of a <hi>Mediatour</hi> to paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie his anger, doth of himſelf either for ſome time forbear, or wholly forgive, as the <hi>Socinians</hi> poſitively affirm that he <hi>hath</hi> done, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny both <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>others,</hi> ſay (but for his purpoſe and decree) he <hi>might have done.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:119845:19"/>
            <p>So that if this be all the <hi>Dowry</hi> of the <hi>Heathens,</hi> neither true faith nor ſalvation may be entailed upon it, and will be but the <hi>Concubines, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens gifts,</hi> but will fall ſhort of the <hi>free-womans heirs inheritance;</hi> It was of old, <hi>Faith in a Meſſiah to come, and in Jeſus Chriſt now that he is come,</hi> that ever did, doth, or will bring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to ſalvation. And although they who are otherwiſe minded, may ſeem the more <hi>candid</hi> and <hi>charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> yet I muſt account it not <hi>pity</hi> but <hi>folly and pride,</hi> to make our ſelves more merciful and wiſe then <hi>God;</hi> and that therefore S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> was more <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gredendum eſt nemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ullâ unquam at ate ad ſpiritualem Jeruſalem perveniſſe, niſi cui di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinitùs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velatus fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erit unus Mediator Dei &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum, &amp;c</hi> De Civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat. Dei l. 18. cap. 47</note> ſound in the faith, who makes this one <hi>Article</hi> of it. That it is to be believed, that none ever belonged to the ſpiritual <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to whom Chriſt was not revealed, as Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour; which he looks at as ſo Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental a truth, and which he was ſo fully poſſeſſed with, that he is not affraid to ſpeak a very great word, and if I tell you it, I hope you will not be offended at it. It is this. <hi>Qui dicit hominem ſervari poſſe ſine Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto, dubito an ipſe per Chriſtum ſervari poteſt.</hi> He doubteth whether that
<pb facs="tcp:119845:19"/> man can be <hi>ſaved by Chriſt,</hi> who believes and maintain's that any man can be <hi>faved without Chriſt.</hi> But notwithſtanding all this, <hi>Satan</hi> and <hi>Antichriſt</hi> are deadly enemies to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> would have him robbed of his glory, either in whole or in part, and therefore would have us either not as beholden to him, or at leaſt as little as may be.</p>
            <p>And our proud hearts too ſelf-full are loath to go out of themſelves to <hi>Chriſt.</hi> His imputed righteouſneſſe is to us a riddle, and ſomething in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent in us we make our idol. Something in us ſome way our own. The <hi>Phariſees</hi> and <hi>Jewes</hi> of old, and
<note place="margin">Rom. 10. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Pelagius,</hi> with all his <hi>heirs</hi> and <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies</hi> in their ſeveral ſhapes to this day, they would have ſome way or other to commend us to <hi>God.</hi> And ſo out of an over-weening of a <hi>ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moral righteouſneſſe</hi> which they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore, and out of a fond pity of <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers</hi> and others whom they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire, they cannot be perſwaded but that many ſuch might be <hi>ſaved</hi> without faith in our <hi>only Savior.</hi> The more full clearing of wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch point I muſt in the following Enquiry refer
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:119845:20"/> to another place, and for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent cloſe all with ſome <hi>Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. If no <hi>ſalvation but by Chriſt;</hi> then <hi>Calvins</hi> inference is <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ergo patres veteris Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtamenti e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſdem Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demptioris Incarnatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne &amp; Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſione ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vati ſunt. Auguſtin Ep.</hi> 157.</note> good, that <hi>Believers under the Old Teſtament and the New, have one and the ſame common Saviour,</hi> they all <hi>drank of the ſame ſpiritual rock that followed them, and that Rock was Chriſt, 1 Cor.</hi> 10. 3, 4. Our <hi>Chriſt</hi> was their <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> the <hi>precious foundation, corner ſtone,</hi> which did unite both ſides of the building and uphold both, as it was the ſame <hi>brazen ſerpent</hi> which from contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry quarters of the Camp they look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at for healing. <hi>They</hi> looked for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward at him as to come, <hi>we</hi> back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward as already come, but both their faith and ours meet in the ſame <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, yeſterday, and to day, and for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 13, 8.</note> who being lifted up on the Croſſe, and by faith looked upon heal's and ſaves all that ever were, or ſhall be ſaved; <hi>for beſides him no ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in this let us admire and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore the vaſt exten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and unvaluable worth of our <hi>Saviours</hi> merit, that
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:119845:20"/> reacheth to ſo many, and operateth at ſuch a diſtance.</p>
            <p>How ductile and precious is this fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt gold that ſpreadeth ſo farre, and purchaſeth the Redemption of ſo many? Of them in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the world by a price that was paid four thouſand years after? According to mens ordinary rates, its little that they would part with for the preſent, for a payment to be made, or a purchaſe to be enjoyed a thouſand years after. That price therefore muſt be of infinite value, which at a far greater diſtance pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed the ſalvation of ſo many precious ſouls, one of which a whole world could not redeem. For this you ſhall once and again in the <hi>Revelation</hi> have the whole <hi>Chorus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rev. 5. 9. Rev. 7 9, 10.</note> ſinging <hi>Amen, Hallelujah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. With the like humble aw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, let us adore and tremble at the moſt dreadful, and yet moſt juſt Judgement of <hi>God</hi> upon the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then,</hi> the farre greater part of the world then, whom yet he over-look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Acts 14. 16. &amp;</hi> 17. 30. and left in darkneſſe without the true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of a <hi>Saviour,</hi> and ſo without
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:119845:21"/> means and hopes of ſalvation; and i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>ead of flattering them, and thereby hardning others, (by cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out new ways invented by our ſelves, beſides the King of Heavens high-way to life, and not ſticking as ſome do loudly to accuſe God of partiality, injuſtice, and cruelty, if it ſhould be otherwiſe.) Let us lay our hands upon our mouths, when ſtanding upon the brink of this bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſſe depth, we have firſt cryed out <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Lord, who will not fear</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 11. 33.</note> 
               <hi>thee, for thy judgements are made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt. Who ſheweſt mercy on whom</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rev. 15. 3. 4.</note> 
               <hi>thou wilt ſhew mercy, and whom thou wilt thou hardneſt. Even ſo, O Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 9. 18 Matth. 11. 25, 26.</note> 
               <hi>for ſo it ſeemed good in thy ſight,</hi> and what is good in his eyes, let it not be evil in ours.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 3. And as we are to tremble at the thoughts of them then, ſo let us pity the forlorn condition of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans, Infidels,</hi> and <hi>Jews</hi> now; who either do not know, or will not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the only Saviour <hi>which is Chriſt the Lord;</hi> and ſo while
<note place="margin">Luke 2. 11</note> they are deadly ſick, either hear of no Phyſician, or ſpit out their <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick;</hi> though they will not, yet
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:119845:21"/> their moſt undone condition cryeth out aloud that they have greateſt need of our pity and prayers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 4. And God may as much expect our humbleſt and heartieſt praiſes, who hath <hi>provided better things for us,</hi> to whom he hath <hi>made known the riches of the glory of this</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Col. 1. 26, 27. Epheſ. 3. 5</note> 
               <hi>myſtery among the</hi> Gentiles, <hi>which is Chriſt in us the hope of glory, and who hath aboliſhed death, and brought life and immortality to light by the Goſpel.</hi> That hee in whoſe hand our times
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 1. 10.</note> are, hath not caſt them and us into thoſe former Ages of <hi>Heatheniſh</hi> blindneſs and darkneſs, but hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved us to ſuch <hi>times,</hi> and ſettled us in ſuch <hi>places,</hi> in which <hi>Chriſt</hi> and ſalvation by him have been fully manifeſted, freely offered, nay ſtrongly urged and preſſed upon our acceptance. What was <hi>his</hi> being a <hi>Grecian,</hi> an <hi>Athenian,</hi> a <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> to thy being a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> a <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> a <hi>Scholar,</hi> eſpecially if ſuch an one, as ſavingly knoweth Jeſus Chriſt, and how will <hi>his</hi> ſo great thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for the former, condemn thy great ingratitude for the latter?</p>
            <p n="1">1. The mercy being <hi>great</hi> of the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:119845:22"/> largeſt ſize. It is <hi>Salvation.</hi> Now how joyful and thankful was <hi>Zache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> when upon his entertainment of <hi>Chriſt ſalvation came to his</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 19. 9</note> 
               <hi>houſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How much more ſhould we be, if upon our enjoyment and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable entertainment of the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel,</hi> this ſalvation be come to our <hi>ſouls?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>diſtinguiſhing</hi> mercy in it is as great, and therefore calls for greater praiſes, That we ſhould have that which others are, and have been deprived of. How doth <hi>Haman</hi> enhaunce and ingrandize his <note place="margin">Eſth. 5. 12.</note> honour, that he ſhould be invited when none elſe were? That was to a <hi>royal banquet,</hi> but nothing to this <hi>Marriage</hi> Feaſt which the <hi>King of Heaven</hi> makes us, and in which they that miniſter to us, are Miniſters of <hi>Chriſt and ſalvation.</hi> This <hi>non</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 147. 20.</note> 
               <hi>fecit taliter,</hi> rendreth it a ſingular mercy. This made <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf <hi>rejoyce in ſpirit, and ſay, Father</hi> I
<note place="margin">Matth. 11. 25, 26.</note> 
               <hi>thank thee;</hi> and what there follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, addeth</p>
            <p n="3">3. A third argument of greater praiſe, That as it is a <hi>great</hi> and <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uliar</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:119845:22"/> favour, ſo when others of <hi>greateſt worth are paſſed by, it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on them that are more unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, concealed from the wiſe and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and revealed unto babes:</hi> To the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> whoſe ſtyle was that they <hi>knew not God, 1 Theſſ. 4. 5. without God, and without hope too<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Epheſ.</hi> 2. 12. not only <hi>helpleſſe,</hi> but <hi>hopeleſſe,</hi> and ſo (as in our ſelves) wholly deſperate.</p>
            <p>And yet more particularly amongſt them to <hi>us here</hi> without the <hi>Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pick, extra ſolis vias,</hi> in the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt end of Heaven, and in the skirts of the Earth, and might have been as much divided from <hi>God,</hi> as we <note place="margin">Et penitùs toto diviſos orbe Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tannos.</note> are from the reſt of the world; whoſe <hi>Anceſtors</hi> in times of <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſme</hi> were as barbarous as any, if we believe <hi>Caeſar;</hi> and in times of <hi>Popery</hi> as idolatrous and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious as any, nay, afforded more <hi>Schoolmen</hi> avowed Champions for it, then any other Nation, if you will credit either your own compu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, or ſome others that have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the pains to make it. And yet even into this dark corner hath this glorious light ſhined; and then as
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:119845:23"/> ſhe ſaid, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>whence is this</hi> that <hi>God</hi> hath reſpected <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <note place="margin">Luke 1. 43</note> our very <hi>low eſtate and condition? that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">V. 48.</note> 
               <hi>this day-ſpring from on high hath vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited us, which ſate in darkneſſe and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">V. 78, 79.</note> 
               <hi>the ſhadow of death?</hi> The <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> beginneth and endeth the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of ſuch a mercy, with a <hi>Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lelujah, Pſ.</hi> 147. 1, 20. And if they through ſuch veils could ſee ſuch cauſe to bleſſe <hi>God</hi> for ſuch darker glimmerings, how much more ſhould we in the brighter Sun-ſhine? who are either not left in the <hi>Heathens mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night,</hi> or the <hi>Jews twilight,</hi> but live in the <hi>Goſpels noon-day brightneſſe,</hi> &amp; have ſalvation ſo openly and clearly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed and manifeſted?</p>
            <p n="4">4. And (which is yet a further ground of thankfulneſſe) this ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation <hi>only in and by Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Now bleſſed be <hi>God,</hi> as for ſo <hi>bleſſed a gift;</hi> ſo that it is both wrought and kept for us <hi>by ſo ſafe a hand:</hi> for had it been in any other, <hi>our own or others,</hi> it might have proved either ſo <hi>weak</hi> or <hi>falſe,</hi> that our ſalvation might have never been wrought, or at leaſt not enſured. What <hi>Prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gals</hi> we were of it in <hi>Adam,</hi> our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:119845:23"/> broken condition in our ſelves doth too ſadly evidence. But <hi>bleſſed be the Lord God of Iſrael, who hath</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke 1. 68 69.</note> 
               <hi>raiſed up an horn of ſalvation for us in the houſe of his ſervant</hi> David. <hi>Hath laid help upon one that is migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 89. 19. Iſa. 63. 1. Iſa. 9. 6.</note> 
               <hi>even mighty to ſave,</hi> and ſo the <hi>mighty God</hi> prove's the <hi>Prince of our peace.</hi> Hath choſen every way the beſt for us, that he only is our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, who is the only Potentate;</hi> alone <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6. 15.</note> all-ſufficient, and moſt faithful and merciful, that in all our ſtraits we may <hi>ſtand ſtill, and ſee the ſalvation</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Exod. 14. 13.</note> 
               <hi>of a God.</hi> We need no other, we can have no better, none ſo good, and therefore it is infinite mercy that we can have none but him only.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 5. And therefore from our ſouls, let us abhorre that looſe and profane opinion, <hi>that every man may be ſaved in any Religion,</hi> if he be true to it, and live orderly in it. Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained of old by <hi>Apelles,</hi> as we finde <note place="margin">Hiſt. lib. 5. cap. 13. Philaſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ius</note> in <hi>Euſebius.</hi> By <hi>Rhetorius</hi> in <hi>Auſtin,</hi> and the <hi>Lampetiani</hi> in <hi>Damaſcen. Mahomet</hi> promiſeth Paradiſe to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Sect</hi> that liveth lively. And it were well if too many <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in this turned not <hi>Turks,</hi> in thinking
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:119845:24"/> they may be ſaved in <hi>any Religion;</hi> for elſe they would ſtick more firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly then they do to the <hi>true:</hi> The <hi>Germane Familiſts</hi> held the like in the former Age. <hi>Our Church</hi> then curſed it in their <hi>eighteenth Article,</hi> (which is the only one <hi>Anathema</hi> that we finde in the whole number of the thirty nine) but that accurſed <note place="margin">Joſh. 6. 26. 1 Kings 16 34.</note> 
               <hi>Jericho</hi> is faſt building up again in <hi>this</hi> of ours, whileſt all <hi>Sects</hi> are ſo much ſuffered, which (it may be feared) is ſtrongly acted by them, who when they have gotten power, and with it fire and faggot into their hand, will ſuffer none but their own. <hi>God</hi> in mercy prevent and diſappoint all ſuch deſignes: Mean while, let us think, how our preſent <hi>Indifferency</hi> in matters of Religion agreeth with this one <hi>onely way to ſalvation</hi> in the Text.</p>
            <p>Which further condemneth the obſtinate blind <hi>Jewes,</hi> who whileſt they worſhip and look to be ſaved by a <hi>God,</hi> reject, curſe, and blaſpheme the only <hi>Saviour</hi> as an <hi>Impoſtor,</hi> and in their prayers make <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (which is <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Buxtorf. Synag. Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daic. cap.</hi> 5.</note> the name of our <hi>Jeſus)</hi> an abrevia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of that their ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>id petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:119845:24"/> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in which they blaſphemouſly pray that his moſt bleſſed <hi>Name and memory may bee blotted out,</hi> by which only the <hi>Text</hi> aſſureth us, that all, that ever ſhall, muſt be ſaved.</p>
            <p>Which alſo condemneth the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limated <hi>Deiſts</hi> of our Age, who, it ſeemeth, are ſuch intimate friends to <hi>God,</hi> that they can have free ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs to him, without a <hi>Mediatour,</hi> whom yet the <hi>Scripture,</hi> out of him, holdeth out to us, as a <hi>conſuming fire;</hi> &amp; therefore it was <hi>Luthers Canon,</hi> as he calleth it, and which he oft in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culcate's, <hi>Abſtinendum eſſe à ſpecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culatione</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>In</hi> Gal. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Majeſtatis. Gods</hi> dread Majeſty, if not pacified by the <hi>Son</hi> of his Love, will frown the ſtouteſt ſinner into Hell, which will never be quenched but by his bloud. He is the <hi>bridge</hi> by which alone we can paſs over to eternal life; tread be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, and we are irrecoverably plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged into that bottomeleſs gulf, that <hi>Jacobs Ladder</hi> by which <hi>God</hi> co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth down to us, and by which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone we get up to <hi>God,</hi> if put by it, ware<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> a break-neck fall.</p>
            <p>Add to theſe the <hi>compleat Moraliſt,</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:119845:25"/> who alſo prove's the <hi>ſelf-ſufficient Juſticiary,</hi> who looks at <hi>faith,</hi> but as a <hi>notion,</hi> and at an <hi>imputed righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe,</hi> as a <hi>putatitious ridiculous abſurdity.</hi> His <hi>rational and virtuous morality</hi> is his <hi>Religion.</hi> And an <hi>Ariſtotles Ethicks,</hi> or a <hi>Tullies Offices,</hi> or ſome ſuch like Book his <hi>Bible.</hi> Which were he of S. <hi>Auſtins</hi> Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, would not ſatisfie him, becauſe he cannot find the name of <hi>Chriſt</hi> there. But <hi>he that is well, needeth not the Phyſician;</hi> and he who is in his own thoughts ſo ſafe and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat, hath as little thought of a <hi>Saviour,</hi> or of any but <hi>himſelf,</hi> and his own fair, juſt, and ſober dealing, which he claimeth Heaven by. But would ſuch know, that when the gulf is to be ſhot, to claſp their own arms about themſelves is the certain way to ſink irrecoverably.</p>
            <p>Nor muſt we here forget the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts,</hi> with their followers, who have invented many other <hi>names;</hi> as <hi>Maſſes, Indulgences, Free-will, Merits, Pilgrimages, &amp;c.</hi> whereby they hope to be ſaved, which made <hi>Bullinger</hi> on this Text cry out, <hi>Sed O Deus bone, &amp;c. Good Lord, how long hath
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:119845:25"/> this bleſsed doctrine lien hid, and been obſcured, that it hath been but to a poor few that the myſtery of Chriſt hath been manifeſted.</hi> And <hi>Calvin</hi> upon it ſaith, <hi>that were we throughly poſſeſsed with this one truth, it would have ſilenced moſt of the Popiſh Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies.</hi> In which, although they dare not deny, but that we are ſaved by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> yet <hi>dum tot adminicula confingunt vix certiſſimam ſalutis par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem illi faciunt reſiduam. Stapleton</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Stapleton Antidot.</note> here plieth it faſt with his <hi>Antidotes,</hi> as though theſe their inventions were ſubſervient to <hi>Chriſt.</hi> But his <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotes</hi> will never take away this <hi>poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> that many of them are <hi>contrary</hi> to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and derogate from him, and that their <hi>Free-will</hi> and <hi>Merit</hi> ſet their own name, at leaſt in part on their ſalvation, when the Text will own no other <hi>name whereby we muſt be ſaved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 6. And therefore our duty on the contrary, is</p>
            <p n="1">1. Out of a tender care of our ſelves, <hi>if there be no ſalvation but by Chriſt, then above all things to make ſure of Chriſt,</hi> As ever we would make ſure of ſalvation, If ſaved only by
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:119845:26"/> him. O then with the woman in <note place="margin">Matth. 9. 20, 21.</note> the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> let every believing ſoul ſay, That I may be ſo happy as <hi>to touch the hem of his garment.</hi> If he <note place="margin">John 1. 14</note> be <hi>the onely begotten Son of God,</hi> he ſhall be <hi>the only beloved of my ſoul,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>unus &amp; unicus meus, my onely One, my onely Saviour;</hi> and how then <hi>ſhall we eſcape, if we neglect ſo great</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 2. 3.</note> 
               <hi>ſalvation?</hi> And what an over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelming confuſion ſhall we lie un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, if <hi>Chriſt</hi> our <hi>Saviour</hi> finding us yet in our ſins, ſhall ſay to us, <hi>quae utilitas in ſanguine meo?</hi> As for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny profit or benefit that we through <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ambroſ. de virgin. l.</hi> 3.</note> our neglect of it, ſhall gain by it? were there but one onely remedy for ſome deadly diſeaſe that we are ſick of, if it might be had, we would not reſt till we had got the receipt of it, and made uſe of it; O let us not be more careful of our bodies then of our ſouls, or for the health and life of the one then for the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſalvation of the other. <hi>How ſick of love</hi> ſhould the faint <hi>Spouſe</hi> be for her <hi>onely beloved?</hi> That ſhe may
<note place="margin">Cant. 2. 5.</note> once be able to embrace him, and ſay, <hi>My Beloved is mine, and I am</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ver. 16.</note> 
               <hi>his.</hi> What ever it coſt's me, my ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:119845:26"/> lieth upon it, and therefore through all difficulties and dangers, I will make out after him, and not reſt till I enjoy him; and if in this purſuit <hi>I periſh, I periſh.</hi> Let me pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh for him, who am ſure to periſh everlaſtingly without him. This in care of our ſelves.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But upon this account ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing it is, yea very much that we owe in way of gratitude to him.</p>
            <p>1<hi rend="sup">o</hi> As he is our onely One, ſo let the chaſt Spouſe be his, <hi>Cant. 6. 9<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> onely for him, and not for another, Hoſ.</hi> 3. 3. The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> telleth us that he <hi>died</hi> for this very end, that <hi>wee might not live to our ſelves, but to him,</hi> 2 Cor. 5. 15.</p>
            <p>2<hi rend="sup">o</hi> And as we in and by him en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy that peculiar and ſingular bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, which (as we heard) the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt of the <hi>Heathens</hi> fell ſhort of, ſo let us be a <hi>peculiar people</hi> to him, do <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 9. Matth. 5. 47.</note> ſome <hi>ſingular thing</hi> for him, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to outſtrip them as much in performance of duty, as we doe in enjoyment of mercy; at leaſt let us not in <hi>the light</hi> ſtumble in that way, wherein they walked more upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>in the dark,</hi> by being <hi>worſe</hi> then <note place="margin">2 Chro 9.</note>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:119845:27"/> they, which the <hi>Prophet Ezekiel</hi> ſadly <note place="margin">Ezek. 16. 47, 48. 51.</note> bewailed in his time, and <hi>Salvian</hi> in his. O be aſhamed that the <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality</hi> of a <hi>Pagan</hi> ſhould out-ſtrip the <hi>Religion of a Chriſtian,</hi> that our rebellions ſhould <hi>juſtifie</hi> their abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations. <note place="margin">Ezek. 16. 51, 52. M. <hi>Pemble.</hi>
               </note> For (as <hi>He</hi> ſaid well) <hi>God certainly will ſhame that ſervant that diſhonoureth his Maſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3<hi rend="sup">o</hi> And Laſtly, becauſe <hi>ſalvation is only by Chriſt,</hi> therefore in all mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>ſalvation,</hi> with a ſingle eye let us look to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and to <hi>God</hi> in him, and at our ſelves as receiving all from him, as <hi>Elected</hi> in him, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed</hi> by him, <hi>Juſtified</hi> by his grace, and the imputation of his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, in which is the ground of our comfort, and <hi>Sanctified</hi> by his <hi>Spirit,</hi> not by a <hi>Philoſophical faith,</hi> or the uſe of <hi>right Reaſon,</hi> or a <hi>virtuous morality,</hi> too much now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>days admired and cried up. As of old, <hi>The Temple of the Lord, The</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Jer. 7. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Temple of the Lord.</hi> So now, <hi>The Candle of the Lord, The Candle of the Lord.</hi> I would not have th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t Candle put out, I would have it ſnuffed and improved as <hi>an hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid to faith,</hi> but not ſo (as when
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:119845:27"/> the Candle is ſet up) to ſhut the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ndow, either wholly to keep out, or in the leaſt to darken the Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine, as it is with mens eyes, who can read better by a candle in the night, then by day-light. A profane in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude for <hi>Gods</hi> infinite bounty! To feed on <hi>Akrons</hi> and <hi>Husks,</hi> whilſt the Heavenly <hi>Manna</hi> falleth round about our Tents, preferring a good ſaying or precept of <hi>Morality</hi> found (as we uſe to call them) in ſome <hi>gallant</hi> or <hi>noble Philoſopher,</hi> before the ſpiritual and divine commands of <hi>Chriſt in his Word,</hi> not being ſo much taken with the Maſs of Gold in the <hi>Mine,</hi> as with a piece of baſer aloy found here and there in the dunghil. But what ever <hi>Nature</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ennii Ster<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quilinium.</hi> Col. 3. 11.</note> and <hi>Morality</hi> may be to others, yet to us let <hi>Chriſt be all in all.</hi> Nor let us be <hi>Deiſts,</hi> but <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> let us not take up in ſuch a Religion, as a <note place="margin">Col. 3. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Jew,</hi> or <hi>Turk,</hi> or <hi>Pagan,</hi> in a way of <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Reaſon</hi> only may riſe up unto, but let us <hi>indeed</hi> be, what we are <hi>called,</hi> Chriſtians. It is not <hi>Abanah,</hi> or <hi>Pharpar,</hi> nor all the
<note place="margin">2 Kings 5. 12.</note> Rivers of <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> but <hi>Iſraels Jordan only,</hi> that will cleanſe our
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:119845:28"/> ſinful Leproſie; not a <hi>Philoſophical dull Morality,</hi> but <hi>the Law of the Spirit of life, which is in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 2.</note> that will quicken us to a <hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual walking with God;</hi> not that <hi>Candle-light,</hi> but this <hi>Sun of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nk. 1. 79.</note> 
               <hi>that will guide our feet into the way of peace.</hi> Let all things elſe therefore be <hi>loſse and dung</hi> in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon
<note place="margin">Phil. 3. 8.</note> of this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, this <hi>ſuper-excellent and tranſcendent knowledge of Chriſt Jeſus our Lord; and let the life that we now live in the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gal. 2. 20.</note> 
               <hi>fleſh, be by the faith of the Son of God, who hath loved us, and given himſelf for us.</hi> And <hi>ſeeing there is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther name but this under Heaven gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, by which we muſt be ſaved.</hi> Say we with the <hi>Pſalmiſt, whom have I</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 73. 25</note> 
               <hi>in Heaven but thee? and there is none on Earth that I deſire in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>I. Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert. Fox Acts and Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Tom. 2. pa.</hi> 427.</note> 
               <hi>of theee.</hi> If ſalvation be in none other, then with the <hi>Martyr,</hi> in life and death, let our word be <hi>None but Chriſt, None but Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Tibi Domine Jeſu.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:119845:28"/>
            <head>AN <hi>ENQ<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IRIE</hi> AFTER What hopes may be had of the Salvation </head>
            <argument>
               <list>
                  <item>Of 1. Heathens.</item>
                  <item>2. Thoſe of the old world, the <hi>Jews</hi> and others be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt. </item>
                  <item>3. Such as die Infants, Idi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ots, &amp; diſtracted perſons now under the Goſpel.</item>
               </list>
            </argument>
            <p>THE Doctrine before delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>That there is no ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on but by Chriſt,</hi> is ſuch a <hi>Fundamental</hi> in <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> that whoſoever denieth it, may ſeem
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:119845:29"/> ſcarce to be a <hi>Chriſtian:</hi> and yet too many, who go in that number, can very hardly digeſt it, and are ready to object againſt it. The inſtances of</p>
            <p n="1">1. Divers <hi>Pbiloſophers,</hi> and other virtuous <hi>Heathens,</hi> altogether ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers from <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Patriarchs</hi> and others of the Church, before the Floud, and after it, but all before <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Many <hi>Ideots,</hi> and <hi>diſtracted<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ones,</hi> and ſuch as die <hi>Infants</hi> in the <hi>Church</hi> ſince Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Of all which, they are ready to think and ſay, that its very hard to conceive how any of them did or could, do or can believe in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and yet as harſh to ſay that for want of it, they ſhould bee caſt off by him.</p>
            <p>Now becauſe the firſt inſtance of <hi>virtuous Heathens,</hi> and eſpecially of their <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> occaſioneth the greateſt diſpute, and the other two are brought in but as pleas for them, by their Advocates, I ſhall eſpecially deal with them, and more briefly tou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h upon the other two; and that it may better appear, whom I have
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:119845:29"/> herein to deal with, I ſhall crave leave to premiſe and hint the Riſe and Progreſſe of this Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie.</p>
            <p>Now for this, you know, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though <note place="margin">
                  <hi>In initio: Annaliam apud v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> res patres omnes in confeſſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Caſaub. Exercit. 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>Barouius</hi> look's at ſalvation only by Chriſt, as ſo plainly Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental, and ſo generally received, that he is bold to ſay, that it is <hi>in Confeſſo</hi> with all the <hi>Ancient Fathers;</hi> yet from <hi>Caſaubon</hi> and others, it plainly appears, that</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> held, that before <hi>Chriſts</hi> comming in the fleſh, God
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Homil.</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in Matth.</note> required not the acknowledgement or knowledge of ſuch a <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but that ſuch then as abſtained from I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols, worſhipped the true God, might be ſaved.</p>
            <p>And that <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Stomat. l.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> ſaith, that God then gave two <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaments, the Law to the Jews, and Philoſophy to the Gentiles;</hi> which <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by <hi>which he juſtified the Greeks or Gentiles:</hi> a very high and bold
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>lib.</hi> 1.</note> ſpeech, for which (it may be) <hi>Gela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> thruſt him among the <hi>Apocry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phals,</hi> his words expreſſing much more then <hi>per modum,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:119845:30"/> 
               <hi>Voſſius</hi> and <hi>Andradius,</hi> would inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret him; and much more alſo then his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by which he elſewhere qualifieth it, and (I would be glad to think) revoketh that his errour.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> plainly aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apolog.</hi> 8.</note> that both <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> at that time <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, That <hi>lived according to the rule of right Reaſon, though before Chriſt, yet were indeed Chriſtians,</hi> and in that num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber reckoneth up <hi>Socrates, Heracli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> and other <hi>Heathens,</hi> and join<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them with <hi>Abraham, Elijah,</hi> and others of the chiefeſt of <hi>Gods</hi> ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, mentioned in the <hi>Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> Saying further, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> was that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: upon occaſion whereof, <hi>Caſaubon</hi> rightly mindeth us of <hi>Baſils</hi> Caveat, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as though becauſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifieth both <hi>Chriſt the Word,</hi> and alſo <hi>Reaſon,</hi> that therefore every one that hath the one, ſhould alſo be partaker of the other.</p>
            <p>To which ſome add that of <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Apologet.</note> 
               <hi>O Teſtimonium animae natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raliter Chriſtianae.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:119845:30"/>
            <p>Thus of old.</p>
            <p>And ſince of late, for the <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> and <hi>Arminians,</hi> that they may
<note place="margin">Corvinus in Tilenum.</note> better maintain their opinion of a general <hi>ſufficiens auxilium.</hi> It is too well known how favourably they ſpeak of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> And how <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nator</hi> followeth the chaſe with a full mouth, and like a <hi>reſolute Doctor</hi> or <note place="margin">
                  <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt. Hom. ſpecim. art.</hi> 27.</note> 
               <hi>peremptory Reſpondent,</hi> ſaith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Nego hanc propoſitionem. Nemo poteſt ſal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us fieri, qui Chriſto per veram fidem non ſit inſitus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But of our other more ſound <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, Zuinglius</hi> is eſpecially noted, for what he ſaith of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> as <note place="margin">De peccato Originali.</note> elſewhere in his works, ſo eſpecially in his Explication of the <hi>Chriſtian faith,</hi> (which yet not he himſelf, but <note place="margin">Pareus in Irenico.</note> others put out five years after his death) he telleth the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> to whom he dedicateth it, <hi>That in Heaven he ſhall ſee not only the two</hi> Adams, Abel, Enoch, Noah, <hi>and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the faithful in the Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, but alſo</hi> Hercules, Theſeus, Socrates, Numa, <hi>and others of the Gentiles, and all his predeceſsors, quot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quot in fide hinc migraverunt.</hi> From which laſt words, ſome of our <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines</hi>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:119845:31"/> would excuſe him, as though he meant only of ſuch as <hi>died in the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rivet. Pareus in Irenic. cap. 28. Vedel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nale cap. 9. pag. 106, 107, 108. Prideaux lect. 8.</note> 
               <hi>faith</hi> which it ſeemeth then <hi>Hercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less</hi> and <hi>Theſeus,</hi> according to him had, but the words and diſcourſe to them that read them are too plain to admit of ſuch a <hi>ſalvo.</hi> And therefore ſome others ſay that none of <hi>ours</hi> defend them, which I cannot ſay; for <hi>Gualther</hi> in his <hi>Apology</hi> prefixed before <hi>Zuinglius</hi> his works, purpoſely and at large endeavoureth it. But whileſt he defend's him, and others would excuſe him, I am ſure the <hi>Papiſts</hi> on the one hand, and the <hi>Lutherans</hi> on the other, with open mouth do all fall upon him, railing, and ſome of them jeering, and bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their Scholars <hi>take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eed of</hi> Zuinglius <hi>his Heaven,</hi> for they <hi>will</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Vitus Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcinius Profeſſor Wittenber.</note> 
               <hi>there meet with</hi> Hercules <hi>and his club.</hi> To whom I wiſh no worſe place then <hi>Zuinglius his Heaven,</hi> and then ſhould they poſſibly finde <hi>Hercules</hi> there; yet he would not have his club there to terrifie them. But both parties might well have abated of ſome of their fervour and keen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. <note place="margin">See <hi>Pareus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bi prius.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Lutherans</hi> if they would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:119845:31"/> how moderate their <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancthon</hi> was in his thoughts of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and that <hi>Luther</hi> himſelf hopeth well of <hi>Tully,</hi> and <hi>Brentius</hi> placeth even the <hi>Devils</hi> themſelves in <hi>Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And much rather might the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts</hi> have forborn to fall ſo foully upon him, ſeeing ſo many of their own have ſpoken full out as much, in this kind as ever <hi>Zuinglius</hi> did. <hi>Caſſalius</hi> one of the <hi>Council of Trent,</hi> leaveth it free to us which way to take, ſeeing their Church had not determined it, as indeed the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Trent</hi> doth not ſpeak out in this point. And it is well known, that in that Council whileſt ſitting, a <hi>Franciſcan</hi> in his Sermon to them, proved the <hi>Gentiles Advocate,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sleidan ad ann.</hi> 1552.</note> their cenſure. I am ſure that <hi>Soto</hi> and <hi>Vega,</hi> two of their great <hi>Divines</hi> in that Council, in the main are clearly of <hi>Zuinglius</hi> his judgement; and that <hi>Andradius</hi> a third of great note amongſt them in his <hi>Orthodox Explications,</hi> (wherein ſeemeth to explain what their mind and judgment was) ſpeaks out <hi>Zuing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> his opinion to the full, and that
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:119845:32"/> with more copiouſneſſe and earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. <hi>Seiſsellus</hi> another of theirs <note place="margin">See <hi>Collii lib. 1. cap. 11, 12. de animabus paganorum.</hi>
               </note> makes two ſorts of the better Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, <hi>viz.</hi> of ſuch as with their whole might ſought and worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped God, and perfectly fulfilled the <hi>Law of Nature:</hi> and ſuch accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his account went bolt-right up to Heaven. And for the ſecond ſort of others of them, which kept the Law of Nature too, but did not ſo earneſtly ſeek after God, although (as he thinks) they got not to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, yet they eſcaped Hell, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out puniſhment and pain were in ſome other place they cannot tell where. The <hi>Colonien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es</hi> wrote a Book <hi>de ſalute Ariſtotel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> And
<note place="margin">Balaei Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue &amp;C. Agrippa. Chemnit: exam:</note> 
               <hi>Thamnerus</hi> ſaith, <hi>that</hi> Ariſtotle <hi>was Chriſts ſore-runner, in naturalibus, as</hi> John Baptiſt <hi>was in gratuitis,</hi> and accordingly maintained his opinion <hi>de Fide &amp; ſalute Philoſophica, ſine verbo Dei, &amp; ſine ſpiritu ſancto;</hi> and accordingly <hi>Bruno</hi> maintaineth it, that <hi>ſatis erat Gentibus ſi crederent quod Creator unus eſſet, &amp; ſingulis pro eorum actibus retribuerit:</hi> only <hi>Rikel</hi> addeth, <hi>dummodo implicitam habuerint fidem de adventu &amp; incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natione
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:119845:32"/> Chriſti,</hi> which <hi>Zuinglius</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver excluded. So that <hi>Eraſmus</hi> in compariſon of ſome of theſe, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his facetious temper, was but in jeaſt, when he ſaid that he could hardly forbear ſaying <hi>ſancte</hi>
               <note place="margin">In praefat. ad quaeſt:</note> 
               <hi>Socrates, ora pro nobis;</hi> or if he were in good earneſt, it was<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> not ſo much to adore <hi>Socrates</hi> his Saintſhip, as to
<note place="margin">Tuſcul: Non tam ex animi ſui ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiâ, quam Romanae mercatur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dedae causâ. M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntacut. Analect. pa. 77. In lib. 18. cap. 47. de Civit. Dei.</note> deride many of the Popiſh Saints, as thinking that <hi>Socrates</hi> was a better Saint then many of thoſe whom the <hi>Pope</hi> hath Canonized: To all the former I only add one more, who is <hi>L. Vives,</hi> who ſpeaks as loud in this cauſe as any, and ſaith, that <hi>qui ex Gentilibus naturam ſequebantur d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem.</hi> The <hi>Gentiles</hi> who followed only the guidance of <hi>Nature, were as pleaſing to God as the</hi> Jews, <hi>who o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eyed the Law, and maketh only this difference, that the</hi> Jew <hi>was like a tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellour who travelleth by his Map, the</hi> Gentile <hi>like him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ho goeth his journey by his own knowledge and memory,</hi> and ſo thereby makes him the more skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful travellour. <hi>And that thoſe now who in the remoteſt parts of the Earth hear not of Chriſt, but love God and their neighbour,</hi> (ſuch of them no
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:119845:33"/> doubt he will finde in ſome <hi>Nova Atlantis,</hi> or <hi>Eutopia) want nothing but water, having received the ſame Spirit that the very Apoſtles had, to whom their Conſcience is their Law,</hi> and to whom he applieth that in the Pſalm, <hi>Memor eſt in nocte nominis Dei, &amp; cuſtodit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>egem ejus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that although <hi>Zuinglius</hi> was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy, in a more harſh expreſſion, &amp; in his inſtancing more particularly in <hi>Hercules, Theſeus, &amp;c.</hi> yet hee needed not have been ſo harſhly dealt with, eithen by the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> or <hi>Papiſts,</hi> ſeeing that ſo great <hi>Names</hi> of both their parties were of his opinion.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> But for the opinion it ſelf; if ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>Text, there be no ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion but by Chriſt,</hi> what ſhall we think of thoſe <hi>Heathens</hi>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that never knew <hi>Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> For Anſwer whereto, </p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, I would premiſe this, that I would be very loth to undergo a
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>N. Culver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel</hi> of the light of Nature, <hi>ca. 18. pa.</hi> 208</note> late <hi>Authors</hi> imperious check, which he giveth to ſome, whoſe <hi>cenſure</hi> (he ſaith) <hi>is too harſh and rigid,</hi> (it may be his is ſo of them) <hi>who as if they were Judges of eternal life and death, damn</hi> Plato <hi>and</hi> Ariſtotle <hi>without
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:119845:33"/> queſtion, and do as confidently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce they are in Hell, as if they ſaw them flaming there.</hi> And therefore I could ſay, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence were the beſt anſwer; and ſo that their <hi>Morality</hi> may not be cried up for good <hi>Divinity,</hi> and their vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues idolized to the diſſervice of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the diſparagement of his <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Goſpel,</hi> for me they ſhall ſleep quiet in their duſt; Ile not rake in their graves, but let them <hi>ſtand or fall to their own maſter,</hi> only for his glory, I now muſt, and ſhall always believe and openly profeſs, that if this their <hi>Lord and Maſter</hi> be not <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt,</hi> or <hi>God in him,</hi> they are fallen irrecoverably.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This I premiſe in the ſecond place, that under the name of thoſe <hi>Heathens, Gentiles,</hi> and <hi>Pagans,</hi> which we enquire after, are not to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, all that lived before the Floud, or before the giving of the <hi>Law of Moſes,</hi> and are uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally (though untruly) accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to have been under the <hi>Law of Nature;</hi> for in <hi>Seths</hi> line the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>God</hi> was continued, and ſo in <hi>Sems</hi> after the <hi>Floud,</hi> and ſo in <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:119845:34"/> Iſaaks,</hi> and <hi>Jacobs</hi> afterward; nor will I reſtrain all ſaving know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to <hi>Abrahams,</hi> and <hi>Iſaaks</hi> ſeed of promiſe, although the Scripture is more plain about <hi>Eſau, Heb.</hi> 12. ſome <hi>Divines</hi> are not without hopes of <hi>Iſhmael;</hi> but however it was with their perſons, yet <hi>Abraham</hi> ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing his family, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18. 19. I dare not deny, but that ſome of both <hi>Iſhmaels,</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi>'s race, and of thoſe children which <hi>Abraham</hi> had by <hi>Keturah, Gen.</hi> 25. 1, 2. might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain for ſome time what they had learnt of their pious <hi>Anceſtors;</hi> but they deceaſing, other generations roſe up which knew not the <hi>Lord,</hi> (like that <hi>Judges</hi> 2. 7. 10. and the further the deſcent went, the more they fell off from God, and as the greateſt ſound faileth by little and little, and at laſt comes to nothing, ſo here at laſt they came quite to loſe the ſight of Land, and the light of that even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing growing leſſe and leſſe, at laſt cloſed up in a dark night of Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, Idolatry, or Atheiſm) eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally after <hi>God</hi> had made choice of <hi>Iſrael</hi> as his peculiar people, and fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced them in by the <hi>pale</hi> of his <hi>Law</hi>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:119845:34"/> given to them; other Nations grown then into greater impiety, were more fully <hi>excluded by the wall of partition, Epheſ.</hi> 2. 14. and excepting ſome few <hi>Proſelytes,</hi> and by name <hi>Naaman,</hi> and the <hi>Ninivites,</hi> and <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> and <hi>Cornelius,</hi> (whom they mention as inſtances, all which if ſaved, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lived among the people of God, as <hi>Cornelius,</hi> had <hi>Prophets</hi> of God with them, as <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> and the <hi>Ninivites,</hi> or came to the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet,</hi> as <hi>Naaman,</hi> and ſo had means of ſaving knowledge;) The reſt, for any thing we know, continued in their blindneſſe and ignorance: Now if ſuch, in thoſe times, and at ſuch a diſtance from the godly <hi>Patriarchs,</hi> when <hi>Iſrael</hi> was a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct people of God, ſevered from the reſt of the world, when <hi>Poets</hi> and <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> and the <hi>Devil</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf were their <hi>Oracles</hi> and guides; of ſuch (I ſay) is this queſtion eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially to be underſtood.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This I alſo pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>miſe that this Queſtion is to be underſtood, not of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Collius áe animabus Pagano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, l. 1. cap.</hi> 3.</note> thoſe more abominable <hi>Pagans,</hi> who did proſtitute themſelves to all wickedneſſe and uncleanneſſe, who
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:119845:35"/> are generally given for loſt, and find no Patrons to defend or excuſe them; but of the more ſober and virtuous <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> and other <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens,</hi> who after their faſhion wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip <hi>God,</hi> and lived (as their Books tell us, and many amongſt us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve) piouſly and virtuouſly, and ſo they come to have ſo many <hi>Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Nor in this Diſcourſe do I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to diſpute, whether thoſe more refined <hi>Heathens</hi> did attain to any true <hi>moral virtues,</hi> (I mean <hi>moral,</hi> as oppoſed to ſuch as are truly <hi>Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical)</hi> which Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> up and down in his diſputes with the <hi>Pela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gians,</hi> conſtantly denieth, (whom <hi>Proſper,</hi> and
<note n="*" place="margin">De Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat. Chriſti cap. 25, 26, 27. Lib. 1. à capite 4. ad 10. Joh. 4. 17.</note> 
               <hi>Fulgentius</hi> his Scholars <note place="margin">De vocat. gent. l. 1.</note> and others follow) but many of the <hi>Ancients</hi> ſeem to affirm, and <hi>Collius</hi> at large endeavoureth to make good. That which I am now to enquire after, is, whether they attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to any ſuch ſaving virtue or grace, which only commeth by <hi>Chriſt</hi> our <hi>Saviour,</hi> that thereby we may probably conclude for their <hi>ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Now as to that, in the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:119845:35"/> I muſt ſay, that I dare not deny, but that ſome who (as for their birth and place of abode) were <hi>Heathen,</hi> might be ſaved; for I confine not <hi>Grace and Salvation</hi> (no not in the time of the <hi>Law,</hi> when <hi>Iſrael</hi> was the only <hi>People</hi> of <hi>God)</hi> within the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Civi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Dei lib. 18. cap.</hi> 47. See <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min. de verbo Dei non ſcripto lib. 4. ca.</hi> 4.</note> bounds of <hi>Paleſtina.</hi> Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> dare boldly affirm, that the Jews themſelves, (who yet were ſufficient <hi>Monopolizers</hi> of their own priviledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es) durſt not ſay, that none beſides themſelves belonged to <hi>God. Popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus enim ex verá, qui propriè Populus Dei diceretur, nullus alius fuit; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines autem in aliis Gentibus fuiſſe, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gare</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>In Apologia.</hi> To theſe <hi>Genebrard</hi> adds <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh</hi> in <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, Nahor</hi> and <hi>Laban</hi> in <hi>Meſopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamia, Jobs</hi> three friends, &amp; <hi>Elihu</hi> in <hi>Arabia,</hi> with the ſons of <hi>Ketura, Iſhmael,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Nini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites. Epiſt.</hi> 99.</note> 
               <hi>non poſſint.</hi> As he inſtanceth in <hi>Job,</hi> who was neither <hi>Jew,</hi> nor <hi>Proſelyte,</hi> to whom <hi>Gualther</hi> addeth <hi>Melchizedek the Jebuſite, Abimelech the Egyptian,</hi> (or rather <hi>Canaanite) Jethro the Midianite, Naaman the Syrian, Nebuchadonozor the Chalde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, and the Eunuch Ethiopian, with ſome few others. Qui vel apparent in Scripturis, vel in genere humano la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent,</hi> as <hi>Auſtin</hi> elſewhere expreſſeth it; eſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cially ſuch as lived near to the people of God, or with whom <hi>Abraham,</hi> or other the Patriarchs, or
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:119845:36"/> Prophets of God ſojourned, and ſo had ſome more light from them: As <hi>another</hi> of our own ſaith, we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Montacut. Analect. p.</hi> 22. In which account come <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chizedek, Job,</hi> and moſt of thoſe which they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in out of the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> not, <hi>quin ad alios interdum ſcin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillaverit lux illa Iſraelis, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quando è vicinis praecipuè Gentibus, &amp; conterminis Iſraelis, hunc vel illum, unum alium,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiaverit, modis multis, miris, extra ordinem,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>quia placuit, tanquam aliud ſubinde agens.</hi> This we grant, but what is this to the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to the reſt and greateſt part of the world, more remote from <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea,</hi> and yet farther off from the leaſt hearſay of a <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> of whom (as it was with the poor <hi>Americans,</hi> and many others in the then habitable parts of the world) they never thought, <hi>nè per febrem uuquam ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niarunt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. If any ſhall importunately urge, that ſome of the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther virtuous <hi>Heathens</hi> were in the number of theſe ſaved ones, I ſhall as peremptorily averre, that if they were ſaved, (of w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> more hereafter) it was only in and by our alone <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour;</hi> for my <hi>Text</hi> will abide for ever moſt true and certain, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:119845:36"/> him there is no <hi>Saviour</hi> or <hi>Salvation.</hi> So <hi>Auſtin, In &amp; ſub le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Coutra Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian l. 4. c.</hi> 3</note> 
               <hi>naturali viventes ſalutem nonnulli ſunt adepti, non tamen ex vi naturalis legis;</hi> and even <hi>Zuinglius</hi> himſelf, who (as we ſhewed) thinks ſome of them were ſaved, yet maintain's it to have been by Jeſus Chriſt; <hi>per</hi> 
               <note place="margin">De peccat. Orig. pag. 118, 119. In Apologia</note> 
               <hi>Chriſtum enim accedere oportet quicun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ad Deum veniunt, unde Socerum Moſis, &amp;c.</hi> And ſo <hi>Gualther</hi> teſtifieth of him. <hi>Quoſcunque è Gentilium numero Sanctorum numero adjudican<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos eſſe cenſuit, non aliâ ratione quam Dei gratiâ per Chriſtum praeſtita ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutem conſecutos fuiſſe ſenſit.</hi> Not as <note place="margin">In Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox: Expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat:</note> 
               <hi>Andradius</hi> roundly and boldly, <hi>ſine lege Moſis, &amp; Evangelicâ nobis per Jeſum Chriſtum datâ ſolâ lege naturae permultos fuiſſe Dei gratiâ juſtificatos &amp; ſalvos.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what ever <hi>He</hi> may, yet the <hi>Scripture</hi> acknowledgeth no <hi>ſaving grace</hi> out of our <hi>Saviour. Epipha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> ſpeaking of thoſe, ſaith that <hi>God</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaved men by many ways, but yet meant not this in oppoſition, but in ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination to <hi>Chriſt;</hi> but (as he well ſaith) <hi>Margarita in mari naſcitur,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Montacut:</note>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:119845:37"/> 
               <hi>ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m ex rore coeleſti;</hi> a gemme may be generated in the <hi>Sea,</hi> but of the dew of <hi>Heaven;</hi> ſo if there were any ſuch gemme found in them <note n="*" place="margin">Like that which they ſay is in ſome Toads head.</note>, it was not from the Sea of this world, but from <hi>Heavens</hi> influence; not from the ſtrength of <hi>nature,</hi> or their <hi>Free-will,</hi> as though they who were dead in ſin, could riſe up out of the grave, and walk, and work o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t their ſalvation; It was not <hi>Juſtin Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Of which (as he ſaith) all partaked, not their right uſe of right <hi>Reaſon,</hi> or their practiſe of their <hi>moral virtues,</hi> that could bring them to Heaven, which even a <hi>Chriſtians graces,</hi> as they are preſcinded from <hi>Chriſt</hi> cannot do; if either of them be ſaved, it is becauſe <hi>God</hi> in <hi>Chriſt</hi> forgave both. I ſay, it was by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which (it may be) none of thoſe who are their greateſt Advocates, will much deny: and therefore</p>
            <p n="7">7. I add in the ſeventh place, as, if this ever was, it muſt be by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſo by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in ſome <hi>meaſure,</hi> and by ſome <hi>means</hi> or other revealed to them; for as <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſo alſo faith in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> is in the Scripture required as
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:119845:37"/> neceſſary to ſalvation, <hi>Ephe. 2. 8. Heb. 10. 3. Acts</hi> 13. 48. This was a piece of Saint <hi>Auſtins</hi> Creed, That none belonged to the ſpiritual <hi>Jeruſalem, niſi cui divinitùs revelatus fuerit Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus,</hi> but ſuch as to whom <hi>Chriſt</hi> was revealed. And ſo <hi>Lombard</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib. 3. diſt.</hi> 25.</note> him, <hi>dici poteſt nullum fuiſſe juſtum, cui non facta eſſet Revelatio vel diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta vel velata, vel in aperto vel in my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterio.</hi> It was not, as though a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive ſhould be redeemed by a price paid by one, whom never before nor after he had any knowledge of. So that <hi>God</hi> for <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſake ſhould ſave them, and yet never by any means, or in any meaſure, ſhould make that <hi>Chriſt</hi> known to them. He muſt by ſome means or other be revealed to them, who being grown up to the uſe of Reaſon, were ever ſaved by <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. In Orat. ad Graecos.</note> him, which made <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> who had ſo good thoughts of their ſalvation, to have this other concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the means of it, that in ſome part he was made known to them: but how that was it will bee very hard (as we ſhall ſee by and by) to demonſtrate.</p>
            <p>Indeed for the meaſure and degree
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:119845:38"/> of this Revelation of <hi>Chriſt</hi> to them who are ſaved by him, I eaſily grant that it is not neceſſary that it ſhould be equall and alike to all, but that to ſome it might be more obſcure and indiſtinct, according both to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral <hi>mens eſtates and conditions,</hi> as alſo to the <hi>times</hi> and <hi>places</hi> they li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in.</p>
            <p>And ſo in the time of the Law un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thoſe <hi>Types,</hi> and through thoſe <hi>Vailes,</hi> we may ſay Chriſt was revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to the believing Jews, <hi>velatâ re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velatione,</hi> by a <hi>vailed revelation,</hi> without a contradiction, <hi>in adje<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>to.</hi> And yet I believe that revelation
<note place="margin">Aquin. 22. q. 2. a. 7. Clem. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lex.</note> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> they had of <hi>Chriſt</hi> was neceſſary, and withall more diſtinct and full, then what <hi>ſome</hi> ſay was ſufficient, as though it were ſufficient for them to believe God to be <hi>liberatorem ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum modos ſibi placitos, their deliverer by ſome means or other, which he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,</hi> but they knew nothing of. And as for many of their far-fetched <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences,</hi> and ſtrange <hi>implications</hi> of their <hi>implicit Faith</hi> before mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, I may boldly ſay they were ſo large, as would wrap up in the <hi>bun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of life;</hi> not only their <hi>Philoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers,</hi>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:119845:38"/> and other more <hi>virtuous</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, but alſo the whole bulk of the <hi>Heathen,</hi> if not the worſt of them, whom yet they themſelves would have excluded from this pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge. Mean while we muſt hold, that if they can prove, that any of them were ſaved, I ſuppoſe we have proved, that it was not only in and by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but alſo by <hi>him ſome way, and in ſome meaſure revealed to them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. But whether <hi>Chriſt</hi> was thus revealed to them, and by what likely means it was, this is the queſtion; to which they will very hardly give a probable, at leaſt a ſatisfactory an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer: For although I doubt not of the power of God (which they plead) but that he is able <hi>variis &amp; occultis modis fidem eorum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cordibus inſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lare,</hi> (as they ſpeak) by various (and to us unknown) ways to inſtil faith into their hearts, he being able (as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith) <hi>to do above all that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 20.</note> 
               <hi>we can ask or think,</hi> (which place ſome produce to this purpoſe, though I think not ſo fitly, becauſe it ſpeaks of them who had already believed) yet we are not here to conſider what
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:119845:39"/> 
               <hi>God</hi> abſolutely and extraordinarily could, and was able to do for them, but what either certainly, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably he hath done, and this accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his ordinary Power and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, and in that way by which he hath ordained and revealed in Scripture, to bring men to life and ſalvation. And truly according to this, they were as far out of the way of ſalvation, as they were from the <hi>Church, extra quam non eſt ſalus,</hi> and unto which God uſeth to <hi>add thoſe that are to be ſaved;</hi> and ſo they <note place="margin">Acts 2. 47.</note> were <hi>much out of the way, and ſate in darkneſſe and the ſhadow of death,</hi> Matth. 4. 15, 16.</p>
            <p>And as for the ways and means which are propounded by divers, by which <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Salvation</hi> ſhould be revealed to them, in my weak eye (and it is not an evil one) they ſeem no way promiſing, as ſufficient or likely to effect it. And that for them, their caſe look's as very doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, if not extreamly dangerous. For which purpoſe let us a little take view of thoſe ways that are ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted.</p>
            <p n="1">1. And here not to trouble our
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:119845:39"/> ſelves with thoſe ways of their illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, which <hi>Collius</hi> in his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Book at large inſiſteth on, <hi>viz.</hi> by apparitions of Angels, Saints, nay damned ſouls and Devils, ſuch <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendary</hi> ſtuff is not vendible with us, as being to the Jews, and I cannot but think to the very Pagans offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive and ridiculous: beſides that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of thoſe brave exploits he inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth in were ſince Chriſt, and in places where the Goſpel was Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and therefore nothing to our preſent purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Let the <hi>Areopagites</hi> conceit be firſt <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De coeleſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Hierarch. cap.</hi> 9.</note> conſidered, which was, <hi>that in ſuch of them as lived virtuouſly</hi> God <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways at ſome time or other ſent ſome man or Angel ſavingly to illuminate them.</hi> A piece of news it is, confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently enough reported by him, which it may be he heard when he was amongſt his <hi>Celeſtial Hierarchies,</hi> but is as <hi>Apo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>yphal</hi> as they, and his Books are; for the Book of <hi>God, Matth.</hi> 11. 21. in the caſe of <hi>Tyre</hi> and <hi>Sidon,</hi> telleth us otherwiſe, and that although they had been likely to have proved more tractable, yet they were not ſo viſited.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:119845:40"/>2. <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> therefore <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Strom. li.</hi> 6.</note> ſuggeſt's another way of <hi>Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, preaching to them in Purgatory.</hi> To which I ſay, it was well that they were all gotten into <hi>Purgatory,</hi> and that none of them were left in <hi>Hell;</hi> for there they think <hi>Chriſt</hi> preached not. And truly, if they heard no more of him then they heard from him preaching to them in their <hi>Lim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus</hi> or <hi>Purgatory,</hi> they will be left far enough out of the hearſay of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. This therefore is but a vain <hi>folly,</hi> nay, <hi>Philaſtrius</hi> calleth i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> an <hi>Hereſie.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auſtin de Hereſ. 79. Aquin: 22ae q. 2. a. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. ad 3. De Civit. Dei lib. 18. ca.</hi> 23.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. And therefore as weary of that conceit, the ſame <hi>Authour</hi> elſewhere pitcheth upon ſome other of their <hi>Inſtructors,</hi> as <hi>Hydaſpes,</hi> but eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally upon the <hi>Sybills,</hi> one of which S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> hopeth may belong to the City of <hi>God,</hi> and ſo might direct others to the way thither. Now that ſuch ſome <hi>Sybills</hi> there were (though there be great difference of opinions both about them, and the number of them) what we read in <hi>Virgil,</hi> and others may perſwade. But what they were, I will not, I cannot ſay; but y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> can ſay this, that if the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:119845:40"/> proofs brought for the <hi>Heathens</hi> il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumination to ſalvation, be not more authentick then the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſititious Books are, which now go under the name of the <hi>Sybils pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies,</hi> there would be but very weak proof of their hopeful condition.</p>
            <p n="4">4. If <hi>Balaams</hi> prophecies, which <note place="margin">Numb. 24. 17.</note> maketh mention of a <hi>Star to come out of Jacob,</hi> at which Starre that was lightned which directed the <hi>wiſe men of the Eaſt to Chriſt, Matth.</hi> 2. I ſay, that <hi>that Prophecy</hi> as well as <hi>that Star</hi> was not of an elevation high enough to prove an univerſal Luminary; <hi>that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium in</hi> Matth. 2.</note> 
               <hi>laſt</hi> from which thoſe <hi>wiſe men</hi> came, not being ſo remote from <hi>Judea,</hi> as ſometimes was conceived, and beſides thoſe <hi>wiſe men</hi> (it ſeemeth) were not ſo ſufficiently directed by it, but that they came to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> for bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter guidance.</p>
            <p>But to leave theſe four ways, there are three other which ſome of late have principally inſiſted on.</p>
            <p n="5">5. As the <hi>contemplation of Gods</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>I G. Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi> debt and dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: ſee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo <hi>Collius, lib. 2. c. 13. ad finem.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>works of Creation and Providence,</hi> as though we could ſpell <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation</hi> out of that Book, or that the Sun, Moon, and Stars had been to
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:119845:41"/> them ſufficient <hi>Goſpel-Preachers.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed what the <hi>Pſalmiſt, Pſal.</hi> 19. 4. ſaith of the Sun, and Stars of Heaven, the <hi>Apoſtle, Rom.</hi> 10. 18. by way of alluſion applieth to the <hi>Apoſtles;</hi> ſo that that place ſaith, <hi>that the Apoſtles were like Stars, but not that the Stars are true Goſpel-Preachers or Apoſtles.</hi> I think that in the expoſition of theſe two Scriptures, Interpreters have gone wide on both hands, ſome thinking that the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> did not literally mean <hi>Stars,</hi> but <hi>Apoſtles;</hi> others that the Apoſtle really mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>Stars</hi> and not <hi>Apoſtles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. Nor will that other way be more helpful which <hi>Arminius</hi> inſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth on; that upon their worthy im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of their <hi>Naturals, God</hi> might, and did reveal to them <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Spirituals,</hi> becauſe <hi>habenti da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitur.</hi> But</p>
            <p>1<hi rend="sup">o</hi> That is but a <hi>Popiſh Polagian</hi> ſtrain, to ſay, that they ever roſe up to ſuch a worthineſſe of improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Nature, as might come to ſuch a congruity of merit of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and grace.</p>
            <p>2<hi rend="sup">o</hi> That <hi>habenti dabitur</hi> ſpoken of in another caſe, will not reach this,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:119845:41"/> though ſome do <hi>operosè</hi> endeavour to evince it.</p>
            <p>3<hi rend="sup">o</hi> Should it, we ſhould yet be to ſeek after what manner, and by what means <hi>God</hi> did reveal <hi>Chriſt</hi> to them, which is the thing we are now en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring after.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The laſt way therefore com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth nearer to it, <hi>viz. Intercourſe with the Jews,</hi> by which they might come to partake of this ſaving knowledge, as they might of any other Commodity or Merchandiſe.</p>
            <p>Either by the <hi>Heathens</hi> coming to them, as <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> and <hi>Plato,</hi> and other <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> travelled and traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficked abroad for Learning, and thereby (as ſome think) came to the ſight and uſe of <hi>Moſes</hi> his wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings:</p>
            <p>Or on the other ſide, the <hi>Jewes</hi> trafficking with them might impart this knowledge to them for their ſpiritual cure, as the <hi>Iſraelitiſh</hi> maid did to <hi>Naaman</hi> for his bodily. And <note place="margin">2 Kings <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 2, 3.</note> ſo <hi>Zebulon</hi> and <hi>Iſſachar, dwelling at the haven of the Sea,</hi> Gen. 49. 13. <hi>did call the people to the mountain,</hi> Deut. 33. 18, 19. <hi>as the Scribes and Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees afterward compaſſed Sea and
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:119845:42"/> Land to make Proſelytes,</hi> Matth. 23. 15. And beſides many of the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets</hi> propheſied of other Lands and Countries, as well as of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah,</hi> by which they might come to the knowledge of their duty, and of the means of their ſalvation.</p>
            <p>Nay, <hi>Jonah</hi> in perſon was ſent to <hi>Niniveh,</hi> and that with ſucceſs to their converſion.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Seventy two Interpreters</hi> alſo tranſlated the whole <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Maſius.</note> as <hi>ſome</hi> conceive, or at leaſt (as others think) the <hi>five Books of</hi> Moſes <hi>into</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ehickard.</note> 
               <hi>Greek,</hi> which many of the <hi>Heathen</hi> reading, and believing, and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, might be ſaved.</p>
            <p>In general, the <hi>Jews</hi> were <hi>Feoffees in truſt,</hi> of <hi>Gods</hi> Oracles, and that <note place="margin">Rom. 3. 2.</note> not for themſelves alone, but for all the world, and therefore thoſe <hi>Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> committed to them were called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Gal. 4. 3. Col.</hi> 2. 8. (as ſome think) <hi>the elements or rudiments of the world, i. e.</hi> whereby the world (by the means of the Jews, with whom they were betruſted) might be trained up in the knowledge of <hi>God,</hi> and the things of their eternal <note place="margin">I. G. ubi prius.</note> peace, as they would prove out of <hi>Athanaſius.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:119845:42"/>
            <p>For anſwer whereto, I ſay,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That it was late before the <hi>Phariſees</hi> aroſe, and were ſo buſie; and what then became of all the <hi>Heathen</hi> before that time? And if then their <hi>Proſelytes were by them made twofold more the children of Hell then themſelves,</hi> as our <hi>Saviour</hi> expreſly in the ſame place ſaith it; what proof will thence be of ſuch Heathens ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation? Much like that of the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites Indian Converts,</hi> whom they turn from <hi>Heatheniſh</hi> to <hi>Popiſh</hi> I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry and Superſtition.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As for Zebulons <hi>calling the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to the mountain,</hi> i. e. (as <hi>Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> generally expound it) to mount <hi>Zion,</hi> or the mountain of the houſe of the Lord, to worſhip him there; yet the <hi>people</hi> they called, might only be themſelves mutually; ſo <hi>Calvin</hi> or the other <hi>Tribes</hi> nearer to the Temple, whom they (living more remote in the out-borders) called upon as they came by them in the way to it: So the <hi>Chaldee</hi> and <hi>Piſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator,</hi> or in part be meant of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Nations</hi> which they trafficked with; ſo <hi>Junius</hi> and ſome others, it <note place="margin">A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nſworth.</note> is ſaid, they <hi>ſhould call them,</hi> but its
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:119845:43"/> not ſaid, how many came; and if ſome did by that or ſome other means, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8. 41, 42. that onely proveth, that ſome neighbouring, or it may be poſſibly ſome more remote <hi>Heathens</hi> came, (of which number <hi>Collius</hi> will have the Queen of <hi>Sheba</hi> to be one) and became <hi>Proſelytes,</hi> and joined themſelves to the people of God. But yet what is this to the ſalvation of thoſe <hi>Heathens,</hi> which never had, or heard of ſuch a <hi>call,</hi> and were farther off from the <hi>Jews</hi> in <hi>heart</hi> then in <hi>habitation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. If <hi>Plato,</hi> or any other of them got the ſight of <hi>Moſes</hi> writings, or if others by the uſe of the <hi>Septua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gints</hi> Tranſlation attained to the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving knowledge of a <hi>God</hi> in a Meſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah, let it be ſaid and proved, and we will not Jew-like vilifie or envy them, but rejoice with them in this their happineſs.</p>
            <p>Something we may finde in their writings, (as we ſee <hi>Ovid</hi> in his <hi>Metamorphoſis</hi> treading much in <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> ſteps, as concerning the <hi>Creation, Deluge, &amp;c.)</hi> which we <hi>Chriſtians</hi> may take notice of, as conſonant to the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and thereby gather,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:119845:43"/> that they had a ſight or rather ſome hearſay of them.</p>
            <p>But when in moſt (if it not in all) of their writings, we find ſo much Heatheniſh Error, Superſtition, Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, and many other abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, wholly inconſiſtent with the ſaving knowledge of God in a Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah, which they yielded to, appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, lived and died in; we cannot but conclude, that they were far e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough from ſalvation, if not from the ſufficient means of the knowledg of it; but that for the generality of them, they were</p>
            <p>Either wholly ignorant of the <hi>Jewiſh Religion,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or if they had any knowledge of it, they did not ſo much underſtand it, as loathe and deride it, as wee may ſee in <hi>Juvenal, Tacitus,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p>And whether their <hi>Philoſophers</hi> did not come under one of theſe heads, (ſhould we judge either by their own writings, or by what others write of them) it would require a very quick eye to eſpy that which cannot be ſeen, or an over-large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <hi>laſted</hi> charity to believe the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:119845:44"/>
            <p>3. What the <hi>Ninivites</hi> gained by <hi>Ionah</hi> his prophecying amongſt them, <note place="margin">Jonah 3. 4.</note> 
               <hi>that within forty days their City ſhould be deſtroyed,</hi> (which for any thing we read, was the ſum of his Sermons) we cannot ſay, we indeed read that thereupon they <hi>believed God, ſo as that they were humbled,</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. 5, 6, 7, 8, 9.</note> 
               <hi>and turned from their evil ways,</hi> ſo far as was available to the avoiding of that threatned deſtruction; but whether ſavingly illuminated and converted, is more then can be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; or if they then were for the preſent, yet not ſo, as that thereby their poſterity retained that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, nor more then they did that preſervation of their City, which for their iniquity afterward was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed.</p>
            <p>4. And for the other <hi>Prophets</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies, though I deny not but that ſome of them were ſent to thoſe people, which the Prophets them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in perſon went not to, as may appear from <hi>Ier. 25. 15, 16. &amp;c.</hi> and 27. 3. yet they contained eſpecially threatnings of judgements againſt them for their ſins, of which we read of no good effect wrought in
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:119845:44"/> them thereby. Such prophecies in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed being rather for the informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and comfort of the <hi>Iews</hi> at home, then for thoſe other Nations abroad.</p>
            <p>5. For that inſtance of <hi>traffick and commerce which the Iews had with other Nations,</hi> it is very well known that it was but very ſmall, and not far off. And (except it be of <hi>Solomons</hi> Voiages to <hi>Ophir,</hi> and his traffick with <hi>Egypt, 1 Kings</hi> 9. 26, 27, 28. and <hi>chap.</hi> 10. 28, 29. and that with <hi>Tyre, Ezek.</hi> 27. 17. which laſt were not far off; and of <hi>Jehoſhaphats</hi> making of ſhips, which <hi>were broken,</hi> and ſo ſped not in the Voiage, 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 22. 48.) we read not much, that ſo thereby the Nations might be inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by the <hi>Iews,</hi> who were envious enough to impart to the <hi>Gentiles</hi> that their peculiar treaſure. And indeed the ſituation of their Land was ſuch, and their Ports ſo few, that their traffick with other Nations was not great, and this wiſely ſo diſpoſed by <hi>God,</hi> that they might be the leſs cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted by the Nations they conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. 16, 17.</p>
            <p>So that notwithſtanding all that from theſe inſtances can be proved,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:119845:45"/> although poſſibly ſome few of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> by ſome of theſe means might become <hi>Proſelytes,</hi> or bee brought on to the knowledge of <hi>God,</hi> yet for the generality of the <hi>Heathen,</hi> yea, and of their <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers,</hi> their caſe in regard of theſe two things ſeemeth to be extreamly dangerous, if not deſperate.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That they were wholly devoid of any ſaving knowledge of <hi>God</hi> in a <hi>Meſſiah, whom to know</hi> (he himſelf ſaith, <hi>Iohn 17. 3.) is eternal life.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Rom. 1. 19. viz.</hi> a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall knowledge of <hi>God,</hi> but that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which you read of in the tenth verſe of this Chapter, and <hi>ch. 13. 38. Be it known unto you, by this man is preached unto you forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſins,</hi> is a point not of <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophical,</hi> but <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> Doctrine; ſo that whatſoever is, or may be ſaid to the contrary, the Scripture in this is plain and peremptory, <hi>That God dealt not ſo with all Nations,</hi> Pſalm 147. 20. <hi>That the Gentiles knew not God,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 4. 5. <hi>That they ſate in darkneſs, and the ſhadow of death,</hi> Mat. 4. 16. <hi>Having their underſtanding darkned, being alienated from the life
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:119845:45"/> of God through the ignorance that was in them, becauſe of the blindneſſe (or hardneſſe) of their hearts,</hi> Epheſ. 4. 18. where we have words multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to expreſs the certainty of the things. Their dim Lamp did ſhew them ſome glimmering appearance of a <hi>ſummum bonum,</hi> at a great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; but could not ſufficiently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form them in it, or direct them to it, no more then a candle can the tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veller in the dark, when he is igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the way. And hence were their ſo many multiplied opinions (no fewer then 288) in <hi>Varro</hi>'s time about it. But as for the way of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſtine de Civit. lib. 19. ca. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 22 ae. q. 2. a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t.</hi> 7.</note> by a <hi>Meſſiah, Adam</hi> before his fall, what ever <hi>Aquinas</hi> thinks to the contrary, and ſome others object concerning the Sacramental <hi>Tree of Life,</hi> (which <hi>Chriſt</hi> now only indeed is, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. 2.) knew it not. And although after his fall, and the firſt promulgation of it, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 15. He knowing of it, it is more then likely he inſtructed his off-ſpring about it, as <hi>Abraham</hi> did his family in the things of <hi>God,</hi> Gen. 18. 19. yet the greateſt of them ſoon forgot it, as they did Gods <hi>Sabbath</hi> and <hi>worſhip,</hi>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:119845:46"/> yea, and many other things which were even of the Law of Nature; ſo that <hi>Plato</hi> (as <hi>Ficinus</hi> in his life ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) acknowledged that he had not found out the true way; and <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyrie</hi> doth not like <hi>communem illam</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſtine de Civit. Dei l.</hi> 10.</note> 
               <hi>viam homines ſanandi. Auſtin</hi> could not finde the name of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in <hi>Tullies</hi> writings; nor is <hi>Faith</hi> one of the <hi>virtues in Ariſtotles Ethicks.</hi> And when <hi>Mornay</hi> would ſay ſomething of their knowledge in this kind, me thinks he ſpeaks very faintly. <hi>Adi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verant</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Morn: de veritat. ca.</hi> 27.</note> 
               <hi>ii fortè, neceſſe eſſe ut homo pro peccatis mundi vitam traderat, &amp; ergo Diabolus ſuadebat hominem im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>molandum eſſe, &amp; Civitatis, regioniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que (ſi Deo placet) ſceleribus oneran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum,</hi> i. e. <hi>It might poſſibly b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, that they heard that a man ſhould die for the ſins of the world. And therefore the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil perſwaded them to ſacrifice a man</hi> (a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſome notorious ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactor) <hi>on whom they might caſt all their ſins,</hi> as the filth of the ſtreet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Scavingers dung-cart; which yet <hi>He</hi> himſelf confeſſeth was moſt vain and ridiculous in it ſelf, <hi>ut qui Deum ſibimet ipſi iratum habet, aliis propitium redderet.</hi> That the
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:119845:46"/> execution of ſome abominable ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactor, ſhould be any fit means to lead them to the knowledge and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of a <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> who was indeed a ſin-offering for us, but had no ſin in himſelf, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 21. and ſo was fit to ſatisfie for others; a glimmering of which truth, the <hi>Gauls</hi> in <hi>Caeſar</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De bello Gallico, l.</hi> 6.</note> may ſeem rather to have had, who <hi>Diti ſuo quàm maximè innocuos im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>molabant,</hi> ſacrificed the moſt inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, in which they more encreaſed their guilt, but thought that the more likely way to expiate it. And as for that which the ſame Author alledgeth out of <hi>Porphyrie,</hi> that our purgation is <hi>per principia,</hi> and that <note place="margin">Morn<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> by thoſe <hi>principia</hi> are meant the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> of the ſacred <hi>Trinity,</hi> and that of <hi>Julian</hi> his making <hi>Aeſculapius,</hi> who was <hi>Jupiters ſon</hi> to be <hi>Mans Phyſician,</hi> ſignifying thereby that the <hi>Son of God</hi> ſhould be <hi>Mans Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour.</hi> It may well be his <hi>Moral</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond their <hi>meaning,</hi> or if it were their ſenſe, yet (you will ſay) make's nothing to the queſtion in hand, if you conſider who <hi>Julian</hi> and <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyrie</hi> were. <hi>Heathens</hi> indeed, but of apoſtatized <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and therefore
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:119845:47"/> might well come to the knowledge of that, which their malice could not ſuffer them to believe and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge; but what is that to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of them who were before <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or more remote from <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians?</hi> who either had not that knowledge, or deſpiſed as much as they had of it; and in that other knowledge which they had, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>they became moſt vain and fooliſh,</hi> even in what they accounted themſelves moſt wiſe and <note place="margin">Rom. 1. 21, 22. 1 Cor. 1. 20. <hi>Vide Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium in utrumque locum.</hi>
               </note> acute. They firſt wanted the true knowledge of <hi>God</hi> in <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. And (which was worſe) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ey were poſitively poſſeſſed and poiſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with contrary <hi>Atheiſtical</hi> or <hi>Idolatrous</hi> perſwaſions and practiſes inconſiſtent with the very Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentals of <hi>Chriſtianity;</hi> as how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of ſuch do you find in the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the beſt of them, even of your divineſt <hi>Plato,</hi> who is ſo much admired, and well-nigh adored, and out of whom and his followers, ſo many things are produced as agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to <hi>Chriſtian faith,</hi> that he is half baptized <hi>Chriſtian?</hi> And hereupon when Chriſt came indeed to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:119845:47"/> to the world, he and his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel were by none more ſcornfully derided, and more maliciouſly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed and perſecuted, then by theſe <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> thoſe <hi>Patriarchs of Hereticks,</hi> as <hi>Tertullian</hi> calleth them.</p>
            <p>Such Diſputers had about with the <hi>Proto-Martyr Stephen, Acts</hi> 6. 9. and after the <hi>Epicurean</hi> and <hi>Stoick Philoſophers</hi> with <hi>Paul</hi> at <hi>Athens, Acts</hi> 17. 18. and ſo from <hi>Creſcens (Juſtin Martyrs Perſecuter)</hi> and downward,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſeb. hiſt. l. 1. cap. 15. Graec:</hi> 16.</note> we ſhall find none more frequent and fierce oppoſers of Chriſtians, then <hi>Philoſophers and Conjurers,</hi> the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a <hi>crucified Saviour</hi> was to theſe Learned <hi>Greeks</hi> fooliſhneſs. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t quiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ingenium habet multa eruditione</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 23.</note> 
               <hi>magis ſubactum, it a maximè ei ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det ſimplicitas Evangelii.</hi> And then as <hi>Auſtin</hi> argueth, <hi>quomodo ſunt verè</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Contra Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian: l. 4. cap.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>juſti, quibus vilis eſi humilitas verè juſti? quo enim propinquaverunt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligentiâ, inde ſuperbiâ receſſerunt.</hi> Their knowledge brought them not ſo near, as their pride <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et them off at a diſtance from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſpeaks of <hi>Polemon, ſi reſipuit à vino,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>lib. de Elia &amp; jejunio cap.</hi> 12.</note> 
               <hi>fuit tamen ſemper temulentus ſacrile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:119845:48"/> though he was not drunk with wine, yet he was with ſacriledge.</p>
            <p>And thus theſe two particulars render their caſe (as I ſaid) ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly dangerous, if not right out deſperate.</p>
            <p>If ſaved, they muſt be juſtified, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 30. but that is by the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> Iſa. 53. 11. <hi>Children of wrath they were by nature,</hi> Eph. 2. 3. and the Scripture ſpeaks of no way of reconciliation but by the <hi>Son of Gods love,</hi> 2 Cor. 5. 19. <hi>Nemo Deo, ſine Deo placere poteſt.</hi> Guilty they were, and that guilt could be taken away only by his ſacrifice, and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, and therefore they being out of Him, were out of that way by which <hi>God</hi> appoints, all that do, to come to life, <hi>John</hi> 14. 6.</p>
            <p>But yet let us conſider what on the other ſide, is, or may be ſaid to prove their ſtate to be ſafe, or at leaſt more hopeful; and here</p>
            <p>1. I may confidently firſt ſay, that nothing is ſaid for it from ſound <hi>Scripture</hi> proof, for it no where ſpeaketh ſo favourably of them as our pitiful <hi>Remonſtrants,</hi> and others <note place="margin">Pemble.</note> do, we can there find no ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:119845:48"/> evidences of their ſafe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, but the quite contrary. It confineth Grace, and the ordinary means of it to the <hi>Jews, openeth a fountain for Judah and Jeruſalem,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 147. 29 20. Zechar. 13. 1.</note> but telleth us not that <hi>Plato</hi> was bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized in it. It ſaith, that <hi>they knew not Gods judgements,</hi> Pſal. 147. 20. that <hi>they ſate in darkneſſe,</hi> Mat. 4. 15, 16. that <hi>they knew not God,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 4. 5. that <hi>they had no hope</hi> (what ever we have of them) <hi>living without God in the world,</hi> Epheſ. 2. 12. God <hi>ſuffering</hi> all thoſe Nations to <hi>walk in their own way,</hi> (and that was none of <hi>Gods,</hi> which led to ſalvation) as <hi>Paul</hi> told them at <hi>Lyſtra, Acts</hi> 14. 16. And therefore you may obſerve, that u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually in <hi>Scripture</hi> mention is made of their vices and abominations, as of Rocks in the Sea to avoid them, <hi>Mat. 6. 32. Rom. 1. 21, 22, &amp;c. 1 Theſ.</hi> 4. 4, 5. rather then of their virtues, as to be patterns of our imitation.</p>
            <p>Indeed the Scripture ſometimes to convince the <hi>Jews</hi> of their guilt in breaking the Law given to them, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth the <hi>Gentiles</hi> by the Light of Nature doing ſomething, which for the outward act, were agreeable to
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:119845:49"/> the Law of Nature, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 14, 15. &amp;c. But that make's not them a fit pattern for us to imitate, much leſs proveth that they ſo doing were in a ſafe condition, which is directly contrary to the generall ſcope of the Apoſtle in that diſcourſe, as we ſhall ſee by and by.</p>
            <p>Sometimes alſo the <hi>Lord</hi> ſhameth his people for doing worſe then they, <hi>Jer. 2. 11, 12. 2 Chron. 33. 9. Ezek.</hi> 16. 46, 47. But that is far enough from proving that they did well.</p>
            <p>Sometimes likewiſe <hi>God</hi> threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth that he would <hi>provoke Iſrael to jealouſie by them,</hi> Deut. 32. 21. But that was not while they continued in their Heatheniſh blindneſs, but when upon the <hi>Jews</hi> rejection, they were called to the grace of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> expoundeth it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 19.</p>
            <p>But yet there are three ordinary <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſtine contra Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian: l. 4. c.</hi> 3.</note> places which <hi>Julian</hi> of old objected to <hi>Auſtin,</hi> and which <hi>Andradius</hi> with other <hi>Papiſts, Corvinus,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Arminians,</hi> yea, and <hi>Gualther</hi> in his <hi>Apology</hi> for <hi>Zuinglius,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers uſually produce in their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half, which yet will not be a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <hi>Rowler to bind and ſtrengthen their</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 30. 21.</note> 
               <hi>broken arm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:119845:49"/>1. The firſt is <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 19. where the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (which <hi>Gualther</hi> ſtretcheth too far, when he rendreth it <hi>omne illud quod de Deo ſciri &amp; intelligi poteſt) was manifeſted to them,</hi> and that (as he addeth in the two next following <hi>verſes)</hi> was ſo perverted by them, that it <hi>left them unexcuſable.</hi> But is this <hi>Natural</hi> knowledge of a <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> (of which only he there ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) which they had, and ſo abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, as that it aggravated their <hi>dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi> a ſufficient proof, that they had the true knowledge of a <hi>Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> and that ſufficient <hi>to ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?</hi> No, but in <hi>Gods</hi> juſt judgement (as one ſaith) <hi>they were left as with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pemble Vindiciae gratiae.</note> 
               <hi>ſufficient direction for well doing, ſo without all lawful excuſe for ill do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond is, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 14, 15. of that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The work of the Law written in their hearts,</hi> whereby they did for the matter of the work <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the things of the Law.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon their Conſciences ſometimes ſo far <hi>excuſed</hi> them, as otherwhile, for the contrary they <hi>accuſed</hi> them.</p>
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:119845:50"/>
            <p>But when a true <hi>Chriſtian</hi> cannot be juſtified by his beſt <hi>ſpiritual</hi> works done by <hi>faith,</hi> ſhall the bare outward bulk of their actions, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>faith,</hi> and other due requiſites, be able to juſtifie and ſave them?</p>
            <p>Again, is not this (as I ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) directly againſt the main ſcope of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> whole diſcourſe in thoſe three firſt Chapters? which was to prove both <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile</hi> (what ever were the priviledges of the one, or the accompliſhments of the other) to be <hi>fallen ſhort of the glory of God:</hi> and ſo to lie under the guilt of ſin, ſo that if ever any of them come to be juſtified and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, it muſt be by the <hi>faith of a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore becauſe <hi>Iulian</hi> ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged theſe places to prove that <hi>ſine fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de Chriſti, lege naturae,</hi> they did pleaſe <hi>God, Auſtin</hi> deſervedly tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth
<note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rius.</note> him, that therein he manifeſtly ſhewed himſelf an enemy of the grace of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and addeth that grave and heavy expreſſion, <hi>Hoc eſt unde maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè Chriſtiana vos deteſtetur Eccleſia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The third is that of <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 30. where it is ſaid, that <hi>the ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es of that
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:119845:50"/> ignorance God winked at, but now com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth all men every where to repent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But although our <hi>Engliſh</hi> word <hi>winked,</hi> there uſed, may ſeem to look towards ſuch a ſenſe, as a man is ſaid to <hi>wink</hi> at that fault, which he doth not puniſh; and that ſo <hi>God</hi> all that while ſpared and pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the <hi>Gentiles</hi> in their ignorance, which now he would not, if when the <hi>Goſpel</hi> was preached, they ſhould not, if they ſhould not repent, but reject it.</p>
            <p>And ſo far as concerned Gods much ſparing of them then in regard of outward puniſhment, is true in the thing, as he is ſaid to forgive when he doth not deſtroy, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78. 38. yet it is not the true meaning of that place, or of the wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> there uſed, which ſignifieth indeed to <hi>over-look,</hi> but not ſo to <hi>wink</hi> at their <hi>faults,</hi> as to be pleaſed with their <hi>perſons,</hi> ſo as not at all eternally to puniſh them; for the ſame <hi>Apoſtle</hi> elſewhere ſaith, that <hi>they who ſinned without the Law, ſhould periſh without the Law, Rom.</hi> 2. 12.</p>
            <p>But the true meaning is, that he ſo over-looked (not their ſins, but)
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:119845:51"/> 
               <hi>them and their times,</hi> as not in a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving way to regard them, but to let <hi>them walk in their own ways,</hi> (as it is in that other place, <hi>Acts</hi> 14. 16. which <hi>Interpreters</hi> make parallel to <hi>this)</hi> without taking that care of
<note place="margin">Calvin. Cornel. à lapide.</note> them which now he did in ſending the <hi>Goſpel</hi> to them; ſo that <hi>this o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-looking</hi> is far from that <hi>winking</hi> which they mean. Not a ſparing and pardoning, but a neglecting of them, and ſuffering them to periſh in their own ways, and ſins, ſo that they are wet to the skin under that buſh, from which they thought to get ſhelter; for this <hi>Scripture</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>Gods</hi> wrath and their <hi>damnation,</hi> rather then his <hi>favor</hi> to their <hi>ſalvatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet theſe <hi>three places</hi> are the chief <hi>Scriptures</hi> produced for the <hi>Heathens,</hi> by their <hi>Advocates,</hi> which we ſee ſtand them but in little ſtead.</p>
            <p>And as theſe afford them but little relief, ſo <hi>others</hi> ſpeak ſo ſadly of them, that if they ſhould but ſpeak the like of them who muſt plead for them, I doubt they would judge themſelves to be but in a very doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful condition, and be glad to look out for more grace in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and ſome better evidence of ſalvation.</p>
            <pb n="99" facs="tcp:119845:51"/>
            <p>We may conſider then that it is not from any <hi>Scripture-</hi>evidence that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Heathens</hi> or any for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, can plead their claim to life &amp; ſalvation.</p>
            <p>2. But it is from <hi>proud Reaſon,</hi> which as in many other things, ſo in this, will take the boldneſs to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troll and give check to the counſels of <hi>God.</hi> Though they, whom the righteous ſentence of <hi>Scripture</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn's, may juſtly fear, that all the <hi>Reaſon</hi> of <hi>Man,</hi> will not be able to diſpute them out of their guilt and puniſhment.</p>
            <p>And here the faulty cauſe is eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially an <hi>Idolizing of Nature,</hi> and of <hi>man</hi> principally, of whom as he is in his <hi>Naturals,</hi> they are wont to have too high thoughts and expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, as having looked at <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers,</hi> and other virtuous <hi>Heathens,</hi> in none of the trueſt (but too flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring) glaſſes, of their own writings or other diſcourſes and relations of them, and ſo they look ſo beautiful and amiable, that our <hi>pitiful huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and ingenuity,</hi> what ever the <hi>Scripture</hi> ſpeaketh of them, cannot entertain a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving thought of them, cannot be brought to think
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:119845:52"/> that ſuch richly gilt, and curiouſly carved pieces ſhould ever prove few<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell of <hi>everlaſting burnings:</hi> As <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> to this purpoſe ſaith, <hi>Virtutes Gentilium quadam indole animi it a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectant,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 99.</note> 
               <hi>ut in quibus hae fuerint, velle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, praecipuè ab Inferni cruciatibus liberare, niſi aliter ſe haberent ſenſus humani, aliter juſtitia Creatoris.</hi> Whence it hath come to paſs, that rather then we will condemn them, we will not ſtick to blaſpheme <hi>God;</hi> and in caſe he ſhould not accept and ſave them, we dare impeach him as guilty of three hainous crimes: 1. A <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or of an undue reſpecting of perſons. 2. Of <hi>inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,</hi> in not rewarding their virtues. 3. Of <hi>cruelty and tyranny,</hi> in reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting and condemning them who were ſo virtuous. All which deep and deſperate <hi>charges,</hi> let us a little conſider diſtinctly.</p>
            <p>1. And firſt they cry out of an <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate reſpecting and accepting of perſons,</hi> if they ſhould be rejected who were ſo <hi>virtuous,</hi> whileſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers both <hi>Jews</hi> of old, and <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> how were and are accepted, who had been more vicious. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:119845:52"/> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> upon the <hi>H. Ghoſts</hi> being gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> with an <hi>open mouth</hi> ſaith, <hi>Of a truth I perceive that God is no reſpecter of perſons, but in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>every Nation he that feareth him, and worketh righteouſneſse, is accepted of him,</hi> Acts 10. 34, 35.</p>
            <p>Which objection, although made by many, yet to me ſeemeth very ſtrange: For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. I hope they think that that only is properly a vicious <hi>accepting of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Deut. 1. 17</note> which is in point of <hi>Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> and <hi>Juſtice,</hi> when one is favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and another is diſcountenanced in his right, from ſome extrinſecall reſpects and conſiderations, beſide the merit of the cauſe; as when a <hi>Judge</hi> doth acquit one, becauſe he is his friend, and condemn another, becauſe he is his enemy, when both were alike innocent or guilty, or (it may be) his friend more guilty then the other. It is not in matters of meer <hi>grace and favour</hi> due to nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as even <hi>Collius</hi> their Champion confeſſeth, <hi>lib. cap.</hi> and therefore without injuſtice may be given or denied to either or both, as we pleaſe. So when two men are equally un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:119845:53"/> I may give that out of affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to my friend, which I will not to a ſtranger. Or when two Malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors are both juſtly condemned, the King may out of his Princely favour pardon the one out of his love to him, and not the other, whom he doth not ſo affect without injuſtice. And therefore although <hi>God</hi> be no partial unjuſt <hi>Accepter of perſons,</hi> yet I pray give him leave to <hi>accept</hi> of whom he will in his <hi>Beloved, Epheſ.</hi> 1. 6.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>In gratuitis,</hi> it would look more like a partial <hi>reſpecting of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> if when they were otherwiſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, for ſome not conſiderable cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance, one ſhould bee favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and the other diſ-reſpected. As for the inſtance in the place produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, the <hi>partition wall being now bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 2. 14.</note> 
               <hi>down;</hi> in caſe a <hi>Gentile</hi> that fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>God</hi> as much as a <hi>Iew,</hi> in all things elſe like or inferiour to him, ſhould be preferred becauſe he was a <hi>Jew:</hi> So the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> there ſaith, <hi>that God accepteth not perſons,</hi> but thoſe <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi> now <hi>fearing God, and working righteouſneſſe,</hi> are as well accepted as the <hi>Jews.</hi> But is it not ſtrange, that
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:119845:53"/> that which the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> in that caſe applieth to ſuch <hi>Gentiles,</hi> as unto whom <hi>God had given repentance unto life,</hi> Acts 11. 18. and who had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the <hi>H. Ghoſt,</hi> and the grace of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and now <hi>feared God, and wrought righteouſneſſe,</hi> ſhould bee pleaded in the behalf of ſuch <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers,</hi> and other <hi>Heathens,</hi> who li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in their ignorance and infidelity. How ſpecious ſoever their virtues and actions were, yet</p>
            <p>1<hi rend="sup">o</hi> What worth were they of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt. ad Bonifac. P. Martyr loc. com: pag.</hi> 160.</note> without Chriſt? <hi>Quid tu cum vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutibus, qui Chriſto Dei virtute cares?</hi> as <hi>Bernard</hi> truly, <hi>ſordet Natura ſine gratia.</hi> So <hi>Auſtin: Paul</hi> accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth them but <hi>dung, Phil.</hi> 3. 8. and <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> but as gay cloaths on a ſtinking dead carcaſs.</p>
            <p>2<hi rend="sup">o</hi> Had they in themſelves been of more price and worth then they were, yet could they diſcharge the old arrear? Their <hi>Advocates</hi> forget this, when they ſo plead for them and juſtifie them, as though they were upon even tearms with God, and not originally indebted, or that their virtues, had they been much greater then they were, falling infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:119845:54"/> ſhort of their preſent duty, could diſcharge the old reckoning.</p>
            <p>3<hi rend="sup">o</hi> As though their actions and virtues were perfect, or ſo truly good (as ſome would make them) that <hi>God</hi> himſelf ſhould be a <hi>reſpecter of perſons,</hi> if he did not accept them; Can they ſay, and make it good when they have ſaid it, that indeed they truly <hi>feared God, and wrought righteouſneſse,</hi> as thoſe accepted <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles Peter</hi> ſaith did in the place men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned? <hi>Seneca</hi> himſelf (who I hope muſt go in the foremoſt rank of their worthies) conſeſſeth that in their devotions they did rather, <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem ſequi quam rem,</hi> and then if their fear of God were <hi>taught</hi> and learnt by the <hi>precepts,</hi> and cuſtomes of men, our <hi>Saviour</hi> will tell us how they were like to ſpeed, <hi>Matth.</hi> 15. 9. Indeed we ſomewhere read of a <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonick faith, that uniteth to God;</hi> and ſometimes we hear much of <hi>their ſouls abſtraction from, and dominion over their bodies, of their freedome from paſſion, their love, juſtice, &amp;c.</hi> and we are to think the beſt of all, and for many of their actions wee freely ſay with Saint <hi>Auſtin,</hi> that <hi>non
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:119845:54"/> ſolùm vituperare non poſſumus verùm etiam meritò rectéque laudamus,</hi> we are ſo far from diſcommending, that we rightly and deſervedly praiſe them, yet notwithſtanding all this, without breach of charity, I may ſafely ſay,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That we are not infallibly to build upon what ſome of their <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors</hi> ſay of them; for pictures are wont to flatter, and therefore it would be a piece of too ſimple cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulity, to give credit to all their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations. The <hi>Greeks</hi> had wit and words at will, and could tell how to <hi>Hyperbolize,</hi> and that ſometimes <hi>Graecâ fide,</hi> and when they do ſo i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolize their <hi>Emperours</hi> in their <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negyricks,</hi> it would go hard if their <hi>Scholars</hi> ſhould not do as much for the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> their <hi>Maſters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Nor are we to judge of them by their own ſayings, or writings, which were often better then their actings, and their precepts then their practiſe. <hi>Philoſophi ſententiâ, vita ignavi.</hi> Like <hi>Phariſees,</hi> who were better in the Chair, then in their walkings, as it is not very ſtrange e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven now in the days of the Goſpel,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:119845:55"/> to hear the ſame men to inveigh much againſt thoſe very ſins in the Pulpit, which they themſelves are known to be notoriouſly guilty of in their converſations.</p>
            <p>And that this may not be taken for an uncharitable ſurmiſe and ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, let us reflect a little upon ſome of the fore-mentioned particulars, for which they have been and are ſo much applauded: whereas they are cryed up for their freedome from paſſion, although it be very farre that either <hi>affectation, or morality,</hi> may carry an <hi>Heathen</hi> in matters of this nature, which were their higheſt perfections, and ſo brute creatures often exceed men in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of ſenſe, as being their higheſt top; yet it is well known how great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er preſſures and dangers have unca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them, and put them out of their <hi>Spaniſh</hi> gravity, the ſtorm affrighted the ſtiffe <hi>Stoick</hi> out of his <hi>Lethargi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Apathy.</hi> I need not tell you, how <hi>Cato, Brutus</hi> and <hi>Caſſius</hi> handled themſelves when brought to ſuch extremities. <hi>Seneca</hi> would diſcourſe and write elegantly of <hi>Bounty and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berality,</hi> who yet was notoriouſly <hi>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous,</hi>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:119845:55"/> and that even our <hi>England</hi> in part paid for.</p>
            <p>And as for their high <hi>ſoaring ſouls, Abſtractions from, and Dominion over their bodies,</hi> the very beſt of them are very much wronged, and that by their own <hi>Authors,</hi> if they were not foully debauched, and that with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural bodily luſts, and unclean pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes. <hi>Fornication</hi> not accounted a fault, eſpecially in young men, which ſome think was the reaſon why the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> reckoned it amongſt the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differents, Acts</hi> 15. 29. And even <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that unnatural <hi>boye's-play Plutarch</hi> indeed dare not juſtifie, nor <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> yet dare he condemn, becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ven <hi>Socrates</hi> practiſed it.</p>
            <p>And what ever others may ſay of them, I am ſure the <hi>Scripture</hi> giveth another character of them, and that foul enough, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>not in the luſt of concupiſcence as the</hi> Gentiles <hi>that know not God;</hi> and this not of the baſeſt and worſt (as ſome would ſo put off ſuch places) but of the wiſeſt and beſt of them, as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth from <hi>Rom. 1. 22, 23, 24, &amp;c.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 19, 20. their knowledge in it ſelf being too dark and uncertain
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:119845:56"/> to cauſe any powerful and vigorous impreſſion on their wills and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>natural conſcience</hi> being over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powered by the weight of <hi>natural corruption,</hi> and <hi>God</hi> taking vengeance on their abuſe of <hi>natural light,</hi> by giving them up to <hi>unnatural works of darkneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. But how true ſoever they were to their own principles, or how true ſoever others reports may be of their virtuous carriages, yet in the third place I may ſafely and boldly ſay, they were not <hi>truly good works, or ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving gracès, urenda flammis, non con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denda horreis,</hi> as <hi>Leo</hi> ſpeaks.</p>
            <p>This (what ever it may be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted by any of us now) was of old eſteemed true wholeſome Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Doctrine; ſo <hi>Cyprian</hi> treating <note place="margin">De bono patientiae.</note> of <hi>patience,</hi> ſaith, <hi>Hanc ſectari Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophi quoque profitebantur, ſed tàm illis falſa patientia eſt, quam falſa ſapientia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Hierome</hi> is bold to ſay, that <hi>ſine Chriſto omnis virtus in vitio eſt,</hi> and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>In</hi> Gal. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Theophylact</hi> is punctual and peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>In</hi> Johan. 3. 19.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:119845:56"/> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, He granteth that there may be bad <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> but that there may be any good <hi>Heathens,</hi> he can in no wiſe believe. <hi>Proſper</hi> alloweth them <hi>nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam veram virtutem,</hi> but only <hi>virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum imaginem.</hi> But <hi>Auſtin</hi> the moſt ſerious &amp; faithful Champion of the grace of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> is herein moſt full, ever and anon upon this argument, up and down in his writings againſt the enemies of it; he calleth them <hi>vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes non veras ſed veriſimiles,</hi> nay, he <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Contra Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian l. 4. c.</hi> 3.</note> averreth them to be truly and real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>peccata,</hi> though <hi>ſplendida,</hi> ſinful although they made a great deal of glittering. He doth not believe that <note place="margin">Extra ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiam ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes reperiri non poſſe, lib. de pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tientia. Contra Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian: ubi prius.</note> there were any <hi>true virtues</hi> out of the <hi>true Church</hi> (of which <hi>God</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſaith, <hi>all my ſprings are in thee, Pſal.</hi> 87. 7.) and abhorre's with an <hi>abſit</hi> the very thought of any true virtue out of <hi>Chriſt: Abſit ut ſit ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua vera virtus, niſi fuerit juſtus; abſit autem ut ſit juſtus verè, niſi vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vat in ſide, juſtus enim ex fide vivit.</hi> And ſo in particular for <hi>Chaſtity; Quomodo verà ratione pudicum corpus aſſeritur, quando à vero Deo animus fornicatur? Quis infidelis ita, quis
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:119845:57"/> haec ſapiat, niſi deſipuit?</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he urgeth <hi>Julian</hi> with that of our <hi>Saviour,</hi> that <hi>an evil tree cannot bring forth good fruit;</hi> and when he anſwered that the <hi>Heathens</hi> were <hi>ſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riliter boni,</hi> he telleth him, <hi>aut jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caris vel deliras, qui ſterilium fructus arborum laudas.</hi> He choaketh him alſo with that of the Apoſtle, That we are <hi>Gods workmanſhip, and that we are created in Chriſt Jeſus unto good works,</hi> Epheſ. 2. 10. not brought to them either by <hi>natural diſpoſition or moral acquiſition.</hi> And he telleth him again and again, that he muſt bear with him, if he ſtil object that of the Apoſtle to him, <hi>That without faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God,</hi> Heb. 11. 6. And he would not have him think to terrifie him with the great names of <hi>Fabritius, Fabrius, &amp;c.</hi> for <hi>ſit li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet Fabritius, &amp;c. quorum me nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus putaſti eſſe terrendum,</hi> yet of the beſt of them all he dare ſay, that <hi>voluntas infidelis &amp; impia non eſt bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> that <hi>an unbelieving will is no good will,</hi> nor can any live well, who li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth not by faith in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and that only <hi>hac fide, prudenter, fortiter, rectè ſapientérque juſtus vivit, quia fideliter
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:119845:57"/> vivit.</hi> It is <hi>faith which worketh by love,</hi> that effects any thing that is truly good, and I muſt needs ſay, they have too low thoughts of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his grace, who think that thoſe <hi>dull Moralities</hi> of the <hi>Heathen</hi> ſhould reach that ſalvation, which <hi>faith</hi> only lead's to.</p>
            <p>That they who never truly knew their <hi>firſt fall,</hi> though they bemoan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſome felt effects of it, as the blind man may mourn in fenſe of the pain of that wound, when yet, he knoweth not how he came by it.</p>
            <p>That never knew what Original ſin meaneth, nor the true ſinfulneſs of any ſin, as the breach of a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Law of <hi>God,</hi> and ſo <hi>could never truly repent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Were wholly ſtrangers to the true means of our recovery by <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> and ſo <hi>could never truly believe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Were notoriouſly blind and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable in their <hi>Ignorance, Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Idolatries,</hi> and in a totall neglect (in a manner) of the <hi>firſt Table.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Were alſo manifeſtly guilty of (and yet approved themſelves in) many notorious breaches of the <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:119845:58"/> Table.</hi> So that in their wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings and doctrines of Morality, they made <hi>vices virtues,</hi> as <hi>Ariſiotle</hi> doth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which <hi>Paul</hi> condemneth <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ethic: lib. 4. cap.</hi> 14.</note> as unſeemly for a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> Epheſ. 5. 4. and in his deſcription of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>noble generoſity,</hi> are divers <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib. 4. c.</hi> 7, 8.</note> particulars, which agree not with <hi>Chriſtian humility.</hi> And what in this kind they laid down as rules in their writings, you may be ſure they obſerved and followed in their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes, and ſo allowed themſelves in many open tranſgreſſions of the law of <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vega</hi> their <hi>friend,</hi> confeſſeth, that <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Orthodox: Explic pag.</hi> 207.</note> none of them did as much as they could, although <hi>Andradius their Champion,</hi> taketh it for granted that they did.</p>
            <p>And although for the outward act they did many of thoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, many <hi>things of the Law, Rom.</hi> 2. 14. yet <hi>non omnia, non conſtanter, non recto modo.</hi> Not all required, not conſtantly, not rightly. It would be too tedious and needleſs to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count the many groſs failings which our <hi>Divines</hi> do truly obſerve in their moſt virtuous actions, their righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs being</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:119845:58"/>1. <hi>Not general</hi> and <hi>univerſal,</hi> as it ſhould be, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 6. but although ſome of them were eminent in ſome virtues, yet as foul in ſome vices, as its ſaid of <hi>Cataline,</hi> and is true of others of them who were much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then he.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It was often rather <hi>negative then poſitive, magis extra vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ia quàm cum virtutibus,</hi> many of them were
<note place="margin">Pemble vindic. gratiae.</note> rather not vioious, then virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Or if <hi>poſitive,</hi> yet more out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, <hi>teſte populo,</hi> then inward, <hi>teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Deo &amp; conſcientia,</hi> atteſted more by others, then by <hi>God</hi> and their own conſciences.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Though in ſome (it may be) more inward, that they did <hi>revere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri ſeipſos,</hi> and ſo for the ſubſtance of their actions they were virtuous, yet for thoſe great and moſt material circumſtances, by and according to which <hi>bonum benè fit,</hi> that which is good in it ſelf may be done well, and acceptably to God, they were whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly defective, or rather quite contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: as,</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the <hi>Principle and Efficient.</hi> They were not done out of faith, by
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:119845:59"/> which the perſon ſhould firſt be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, and then the work, <hi>without which it is impoſſible to pleaſe God,</hi> Heb. 11. 6.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For the <hi>End,</hi> (which as it is the goodneſs of every thing, ſo it is moſt neceſſary to be looked after to make our virtues or actions truly good; for <hi>non officiis ſed finibus diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rnendae virtutes ſunt,</hi> as <hi>Auſtin</hi> telleth us) here they were wholly wide; for as the ſame <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith in ſumme, <hi>Daemonibus vel humanae gloriae ſervierunt,</hi> it was either the <hi>Devil</hi> or <hi>vain-glory</hi> that they ſerved in all; it was either to a <hi>bad</hi> end, or if to a <hi>good,</hi> yet</p>
            <p>It was <hi>particulari non univerſali,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">See <hi>Voſſii Theſes de virtutibus Gentilium, p. 258, &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> to ſome narrow particular end, and not (as it ſhould have been) to a more common and univerſal.</p>
            <p>It was not with a ſpiritual eye, fingly looking at the glory of God, which is full in faiths eye, and ſhould be in all our actions, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 31. but rather</p>
            <p>At beſt, at the ſafety and honour of their Country,</p>
            <p>Their own outward quiet, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſatisfaction.</p>
            <pb n="115" facs="tcp:119845:59"/>
            <p>But moſt commonly, and often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times moſt notoriouſly, and affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly, others applauſe and their own praiſe and commendation. <hi>Vicit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor patriae, laudúmque immenſa cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pido.</hi> So that <hi>Auſtin</hi> concludeth, <hi>Si</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Virgil. De ſpirit. &amp; litera, cap.</hi> 27. and <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 99.</note> 
               <hi>diſcutiantur quo fine fiant, vix inveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antur quae juſtitiae debitam laudem de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſimémque mereantur.</hi> I cannot therefore believe, that <hi>Timoleon was a very godly man,</hi> as ſome in the <note place="margin">M. H.</note> Pulpit have here ſtyled him. Nor can I but be offended at <hi>Zuinglius</hi> his <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">De peccat: Origin: Tom: 2. pa: 118. In Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia.</note> when ſpeaking of <hi>Seneca,</hi> he admireth, <hi>viri ſanctiſſimi fidem.</hi> And at <hi>Gualthers</hi> queſtion ſpeaking of <hi>Numa, An ergo tam piis &amp; ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis ſtudiis coeleſte numen defuiſſe pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabimus?</hi> As <hi>Auſtin</hi> deteſteth a like <note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi prius</note> queſtion of <hi>Julians, Erant ergo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnatione ſempiterna, in quibus er at vera juſtitia?</hi> with his <hi>O vocem im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudentiâ majore praecipitem,</hi> which we might alſo return to as bold a queſtion, but in many more words <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Orthodox: Explic. pag:</hi> 289.</note> made by <hi>Andradius</hi> to <hi>Kemnitius, Qui verum Deum quem aſſidua medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatione totiſque animi viribus inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verunt, &amp;c. venerati ſunt, in ipſo om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſpes ſuas collocarunt, illi perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuò
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:119845:60"/> placere ſtuduerunt, illos tu Kem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niti, illa fide, Deique cognitione deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutos diees, &amp;c.</hi> But why ſhould we now labour to boulſter them up, whom their own <hi>Philoſophers and Rhetoricians,</hi> (who better knew them then we can) ſaw cauſe to leave as in a dangerous condition. <hi>Lactan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> had been one of them, and what ſaith he of them and their way, when he left them and turned <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. Quae profeſſio multo melior, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilior,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De falſa Relig. ca.</hi> 1</note> 
               <hi>glorioſior putanda eſt, quam illa Oratoria in qua diu verſati, ſed planè ad argutam malitiam juvenes erudie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bamus.</hi> And afterwards he addeth, <hi>Omiſſis ergo hujus terrenae Philoſophiae Autoribus, nihil certi aſſerentibus ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grediamur viam rectam, &amp;c.</hi> He could find no certainty in their aſſertions, nor true virtue, but argute malice or wickedneſs in their inſtitutions, and therefore he thinks he hath reaſon to leave them, and to betake himſelf to <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> as a better and more profitable and glorious profeſſion.</p>
            <p>And what need then of all that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doe which ſome make to ſtick over and mangonize a <hi>Heathens</hi> beauty, conſiſting at beſt, but</p>
            <pb n="117" facs="tcp:119845:60"/>
            <p>In a bare civil converſation, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out true ſpiritual ſanctity.</p>
            <p>In a dark knowledge of a <hi>God,</hi> muffled up in ſuperſtition and Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry.</p>
            <p>In a bare natural knowledge of a <hi>Creator,</hi> and none of a true <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſome cold affections of love and fear of a God, wholly differing from that which is truly filiall in thoſe who by the <hi>Spirit of Adoption can cry Abba Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Dull Religion! and apt to work the like in them that ſo admire and affect them.</p>
            <p>One <hi>Paul</hi> to me is more then a thouſand <hi>Socrates</hi>'s and <hi>Seneca's.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How dead and wan in a ſpiritual eye is <hi>Heatheniſh</hi> virtue, when it looks out even in its lovelieſt coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, in compariſon of that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine beauty which ſparkleth in a lively faith, and that in the pooreſt, meaneſt lively ſpiritual <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> there is life in <hi>faith,</hi> and but deadneſs in dull <hi>Heatheniſh morality.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that I cannot but account it a moſt unworthy and diſingenuous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude in them, who otherwiſe
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:119845:61"/> moſt of all cry up ingenuity, when <hi>God</hi> in the <hi>Goſpel</hi> hath held forth <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that we may be enamoured with his beauty, ſo to dote upon, and to commit folly with ſuch dead pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, to feed on akrons, when <note place="margin">as Ezek: 23. 14, 15, 16.</note> 
               <hi>God</hi> hath afforded us the <hi>bread of Heaven,</hi> in ſo admiring the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens</hi> virtues, as ſetting them in a ſafe condition, when <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving grace only is held out to us in the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> as the way to ſalvation. And therefore I cannot ſay leſs, then to avouch it <hi>blaſphemy</hi> in caſe <hi>God</hi> ſhould not accept them to life, to impeach him as gulty of a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>an undue reſpecting or accepting of perſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2<hi rend="sup">o</hi> And this blaſphemy higher, if upon this ground he be accuſed (as he is by ſome) of injuſtice in not rewarding their virtues.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Who might moſt juſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn the very beſt of them for their foul abominations, and if their beſt virtues and actions were ſo foully faulty, (as was ſhown in the former particular) if they will needs have them in <hi>juſtice</hi> rewarded, by right then it muſt have been in that kind
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:119845:61"/> which the Scripture ſpeaks of, when it ſpeaks of <hi>rendring a reward to the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 94. 2.</note> 
               <hi>proud,</hi> (for ſuch were they) which <hi>God</hi> explaineth by its <hi>Synonymam, I will puniſh them for their ways, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward them their doings,</hi> Hoſ. 4. 9.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But <hi>God</hi> who is infinite in bounty and goodneſs, not ſuffering the leaſt degree or appearance of it in the creature to go without a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable acceptance and reward, as he would not let <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> go without his <hi>hire</hi> for his ſervice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Tyre,</hi> though therein he inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to ſerve his own deſign rather then Gods Providence, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 29. 18, 19, 20. much leſs would he ſuffer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the more virtuous <hi>Heathens</hi> to go unrewarded.</p>
            <p>1<hi rend="sup">o</hi> Partly in this life</p>
            <p>With inward tranquillity and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bonum a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quod tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porale &amp; &amp; conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiae tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillitas.</hi> Prideaux Lect. 8.</note> quiet of their mind, <hi>their conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces excuſing them,</hi> Rom. 2. 15.</p>
            <p>And outward peace and proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, together with ſafety and honour, which was that which they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves eſpecially aimed at, and which accordingly they were anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in, and ſo as our <hi>Saviour</hi> ſaid of the <hi>Phariſees</hi> in a like caſe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. 5.
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:119845:62"/> 
               <hi>they had their reward:</hi> ſo the virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Romans</hi> and others, had their City and Countrey preſerved, enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, enriched renowned, and their own memories perpetuated to po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity. Thus the children of the <hi>Concubines</hi> were not without their <note place="margin">Gen.</note> gifts, but yet ſent away with them, and not poſſeſſed of <hi>Iſaaks</hi> inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. <hi>Hic ei prodeſt opus ejus, &amp; hic ei addit Deus bona pro opere ſuo;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Contra Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latorem, ca. 22. 28. De vocat: Gent. li. 1. cap: 7. Epiſt. 17. Fulgent. de Incarn. li. 1. cap. 7. Chryſoſtom. ad Pop. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch. Hom.</hi> 67.</note> 
               <hi>in illo autem ſaeculo nihil ptodeſt opus ejus.</hi> So <hi>Proſper.</hi> And again, <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus tantùm temporis vitam ornavit, ad veras virtutes aeternámque beatitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem non profecit.</hi> And ſo <hi>Auſtin. Primi Romani etſi non habentes veram pietatem erga Deum verum, quae illos etiam in aeternam Civitatem poſſit ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bri Religioni perducere, cuſtodientes tamen quandam ſui generis probitatem quae poſſit terrenae conſtituendae augendae conſervandaeque ſufficere, &amp;c.</hi> Thoſe ancient <hi>Romans,</hi> although by their virtues they could not attain the Heavenly City, yet they by them founded, augmented, and preſerved their Earthly, and ſo wanted not their reward here, which was that which they aimed at.</p>
            <pb n="121" facs="tcp:119845:62"/>
            <p>2<hi rend="sup">o</hi> Partly in the life to come, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though not advanced to Heaven, yet by this means they were not ſo deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſunk in Hell; which <hi>Athanaſius</hi> phraſeth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Contra Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian l. 1. c. 3 Vide</hi> Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deaux. <hi>ubi prius.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſometimes by <hi>mitiùs urunt,</hi> and otherwhile by <hi>tolerabiliùs puniuntur,</hi> their torments are leſs proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably as their ſins were: <hi>Minùs enim Fabritius quam Catilina punietur, non quia iſte bonus, ſed quia ille magis malus; Et minùs impius quam Cati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lina Fabritius, non veras virtutes ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendo, ſed à veris virtutibus non pluri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mùm deviando.</hi> So <hi>Auſtin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet for all this, if theſe <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thons</hi> be not ſaved, their <hi>Advocates</hi> dare accuſe <hi>God</hi> not only of <hi>partia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> and <hi>injuſtice,</hi> but alſo</p>
            <p n="3">3. In the third place even of <hi>cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty and tyranny,</hi> for caſting them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and condemning them for want of that which (as they object) they might be invincibly ignorant of; at which <hi>Andradius</hi> fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rcely and <hi>gigan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teo</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Orthodox: Explic: pa.</hi> 291.</note> 
               <hi>impetu</hi> let's fly with his <hi>Neque eni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> diri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as atque inhumanitas te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ulla eſſe pote<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, quàm ſempiternis cruciatibus homines mancipare propter fidei ill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> inopiam, ad quam nullus pa tebat adnus.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="122" facs="tcp:119845:63"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To which bold and direful expreſſions, an awful Chriſtian, whoſe heart trembleth at ſuch blaſphemies, in ſtead of other anſwer might only return that of the Angel, <hi>Dominus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Zech. 3. 2.</note> 
               <hi>increpet te Satana, The Lord rebuke thee Satan.</hi> Or was <hi>Kemnitius</hi> too <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exam. C. T. pag.</hi> 109.</note> harſh when he called theſe <hi>Cerbereos Andradii Latratus.</hi> I am ſure what he after adde's is true; what is, if <note place="margin">Quid eſt, ſi hoc non eſt, ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bum Dei procul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>are, fidem juſtifican<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ludi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficare, &amp; judicia Dei blaſphema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re?</note> this be not to kick at, and trample on the Word of God, to make a mock of juſtifying faith, and to blaſpheme Gods righteous judgements? But for a more particular anſwer,</p>
            <p n="1">1. As though <hi>God</hi> had nothing to reckon with them for but their bare infidelity. As though they had not been obnoxious to Gods revenging juſtice in <hi>Adam,</hi> which deſerved wrath, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 3. and by which alſo they had contracted this impoſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which they ſpeak of; and in this and other their diſputes in which they advance the power of man and free-will, they generally take it for granted, that it is an impious abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity to think that <hi>God commands im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibilities,</hi> taking no notice of any difference herein of mans collapſed
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:119845:63"/> eſtate from that of his primeve inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity. But I hope ſuch an impoſſibility will not accuſe <hi>Gods</hi> moſt righteous commands, nor excuſe their defect or neglect, if it were not antecedent but conſequent to their miſcarriage in their firſt parent, and that not <hi>ex ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannide</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prideau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, ubi prius.</note> 
               <hi>obligantis, ſed ex temeritate obligati.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. As though beſides that, they were not guilty of other actual ſins, and wilful perſonal violations of that very Law of Nature which they might juſtly periſh in, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 12.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And yet further, as though the infidelity (at leaſt) of ſome of them had been meerly and only <hi>negative,</hi> and that they were not at all guilty of any poſitive neglect of ſuch means as they had, and of what they might have done by the help of them; for although the <hi>Papiſts</hi> themſelves will grant, that whatever <note place="margin">Collius de animab. Paganorum lib. 1. cap. 20, 21, &amp;c.</note> thoſe <hi>Pagans</hi> could do, could not bring to Heaven, or even prepare to grace as a diſpoſition to it, yet they might have abſtained from many ſins which more indiſpoſed them to it; and it is the common <hi>maxim</hi> amongſt <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Arminians, Facienti quod
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:119845:64"/> in ſe eſt Deus non denegat gratiam,</hi> and in this very diſpute about <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Collius, l. 1. cap.</hi> 24, 25.</note> it is one of their concluſions, that it is moſt agreeable to Gods moſt ſweet Providence and Bounty, to vouchſafe the light of faith and grace to ſuch <hi>Gentiles,</hi> as did obſerve the Law of Nature as they were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, by which they might come to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting felicity; ſo that according to them there was in them ſome poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, and wilful, <hi>if not malicious neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect,</hi> and not a bare <hi>negative infideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Calvin In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit. l. 1. c.</hi> 4</note> whileſt they damped and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that light which they had, which not only our <hi>Divines</hi> aſſert, but even the <hi>Papiſts</hi> alſo freely grant; and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt others <hi>Ambicatharinus</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring after the reaſon why the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> who acknowledged God as Creator, and in his infinite Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, Goodneſs, and other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections to be worſhipped, ſhould yet fall ſhort of his grace, reſolveth it thus: <hi>Supernaturalis gratiae donis ditandos eos etiam fuiſſe, ni terrenae ſcientiae ſuperbi â elati, hoc ipſum coeleſtis gratiae donum haud diſperiſſent.</hi> That they had alſo been bleſſed with ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving grace, but that being puft up
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:119845:64"/> with conceit of their earthly wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and knowledge, they deſpiſed that which was ſaving and celeſtial, as is evident and manifeſt in many of them, in whom not ſo much igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and negative infidelity, as po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive malice and pride, and prepoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of falſe and wicked principles and practiſes were the <hi>obex</hi> which kept them off from ſaving knowledg and grace; and although for many of them they had not (as we have ſeen before) ſufficient means of it, yet they might have advanced far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and come nearer to it then they did: For <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and the <hi>Church of God</hi> was even then as a <hi>Beacon</hi> or <hi>City</hi> on the <hi>top of an hill,</hi> and what <hi>God</hi> did there, was not <hi>done in a corner;</hi> ſo that <hi>Andradius</hi> his <hi>ad quam nullus patebat aditus,</hi> was an over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſted <hi>Hyperbole.</hi> For they might have done more then they did, and might have gained ſo much know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, as that, although it might not have <hi>made them wiſe to ſalvation,</hi> yet the careleſs, and wilful, and (in ſome) malicious neglect of it, may juſtly render them inexcuſable, and fully clear <hi>Gods</hi> righteouſneſſe in
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:119845:65"/> their juſt condemnation.</p>
            <p>And thus I have endeavoured to clear it from this threefold blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous imputation, in which not only <hi>Papiſts,</hi> but alſo many of our own are extreamly bold and preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, ſo as cannot but make any good heart tremble to read and hear what too often in this kind is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and ſpoken; it would be well therefore that they would be more wary, for if <hi>vera de Deo loqui peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culoſum ſit,</hi> if to ſpeak truth of God in ſome caſes may be dangerous, to ſpeak blaſphemies of him will bee deſperate; and therefore that they would ſadly think and repent of it, and lay their hands on their mouths, and never <hi>open them this way any more,</hi> leſt at laſt when God will be able to declare the holineſs and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of his decrees, and procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings to them, above what they can or will now ſee, they be not left al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together <hi>ſpeechleſse,</hi> when after all their preſumptuous querying of his
<note place="margin">Matth. 22. 12.</note> counſels, he ſhall ask them this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, like that of <hi>Zebul</hi> to <hi>Gaal,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Judg. 9. 38</note> 
               <hi>Where is now thy mouth, wherewith thou ſaidſt, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="127" facs="tcp:119845:65"/>
            <p>There now remain's but a <hi>Plea</hi> or two more for the ſalvation of thoſe <hi>Gentiles</hi> which fell, or do fall ſhort of the knowledge of <hi>God in Chriſt,</hi> and they are taken from the two o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fore-mentioned Inſtances. </p>
            <p>And the firſt of them is of the <hi>men of the old world</hi> before the Floud; Of the other <hi>Patriarchs</hi> after it, and of the <hi>Jews</hi> under the <hi>Law</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many of whom we muſt believe were certainly ſaved, and yet for the moſt part they knew no more of a <hi>Chriſt</hi> or a <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> then the very <hi>Heathon;</hi> the faith of <hi>Chriſt Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour being</hi> no where (if you will believe <hi>Stapleton)</hi> written or made <note place="margin">Nec fidem Mediatoris Chriſti uſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quàm ſcribi in toto V. T.</note> mention of in the Old Teſtament.</p>
            <p>To which I anſwer,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That this bold aſſertion is very injurious to the <hi>Jews,</hi> the then peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>God,</hi> in putting <hi>them</hi> and the <hi>Heathens</hi> into the ſame condition. Nay, <hi>Lud: Vives</hi> (as before was ſhown) makes the <hi>Heathens</hi> condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the better of the two; as he is the more expert traveller, who knoweth his way of himſelf, then
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:119845:66"/> he that look's for it in his <hi>Map;</hi> but the Apoſtle is of a far other minde, who makes the priviledge and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of the <hi>Jews</hi> much more <hi>eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry way, and eſpecially in this, that unto</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom 3. 1, 2, 3, &amp;c. &amp; cap. 9. 4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>them were committed the Oracles of God.</hi> Which the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> before in the Old Teſtament had fully decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, when he ſaid, <hi>That God had not ſo dealt with any other Nation, and as for his judgements they had not known them,</hi> Pſal. 147. 20. <hi>which the</hi> Jews <hi>had v.</hi> 19. and therefore our <hi>Saviour</hi> himſelf faith, <hi>that ſalvation was of the Jews,</hi> John 4. 22. An happy pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge of <hi>them,</hi> as on the contrary (if well conſidered) a very heavy word, expreſſing the woful eſtate of the <hi>Gentiles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. I confidently avouch, that all <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſtin de Civit. Dei, l. 10. cap.</hi> 25.</note> the <hi>Jews</hi> and others both before and under the <hi>Law</hi> that were ſaved, were ſaved by the ſame faith in a <hi>Meſſiah</hi> to come, that we are now that he is come, as the Apoſtle ſheweth at large, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. where, having in the <hi>laſt verſe of the tenth Chapter,</hi> ſpoken of our now <hi>believing to the ſaving of the ſoul,</hi> in the <hi>eleventh Chapter</hi> he ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the ſame faith to have been in
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:119845:66"/> the believers of the <hi>Old Teſtament</hi> to their ſalvation. And he beginneth with <hi>Abel,</hi> who by <hi>faith offered his ſacrifice,</hi> v. 4. as in it by faith look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the all-ſufficient ſacrifice which our bleſſed <hi>high Prieſt</hi> ſhould afterwards offer up for all Believers; and ſo he goeth on to <hi>Enoch, Noah, Abraham,</hi> and other of the <hi>Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs</hi> who lived and died in <hi>faith,</hi> not having indeed <hi>received the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, but yet ſaw them afar off, and were perſwaded of them, and embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced them,</hi> v. 13. according to that of <hi>Auſtin, Chriſti ſaluberrimâ fide etiam illi juſti ſalvi facti ſunt, qui priuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam veniret in carne crediderunt in carnem venturam;</hi> which alſo <hi>Lom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard</hi> averreth to be the joint ſentence of all the holy <hi>Fathers, Sine fide Mediatoris nullum hominem vel ante vel poſt fuiſſe ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lvum ſanctoru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritates</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib 3. diſt.</hi> 25.</note> 
               <hi>conteſtantur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I acknowledge indeed, that the eye of their faith in general was more dim, or that the <hi>Types</hi> and <hi>Veils</hi> and <hi>Shadows</hi> which they then looked through, were more dark, ſo that a leſſe meaſure of faith, and of the <note place="margin">S. Sinenſis.</note> diſtinctneſs and clearneſs of it might
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:119845:67"/> ſave them which now will not ſave us, as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> himſelf aſſerteth, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hom 37. in</hi> Matth.</note> who although he required of them no knowledge of <hi>Chriſt</hi> as neceſſary to their ſalvation, or (as ſome fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourably interpret him) no expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Caſaub. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rcit.</hi> 1.</note> knowledge; yet he addeth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>God</hi> expecting that we now ſhould ſee more in the <hi>Sun-ſhine;</hi> then they could in the <hi>Twi-light,</hi> in which, as many Articles of the <hi>Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> were more obſcurely delivered, ſo they were more imperfectly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended and believed. But as they came down nearer and nearer to <hi>Chriſts</hi> time, the more diſtinctly they had them revealed to them, as the nearer it groweth to <hi>Sun-riſe,</hi> we may ſee the more clearly; and ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Bonaventure, Fides crevit ſucceſſu temporis, non Articulorum</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>In 3. Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton: diſt: 28. q. 4. 22 ae q. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 7.</note> 
               <hi>numeroſitate, ſed credendorum explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione;</hi> or as <hi>Aquinas</hi> hath it, for ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and in the general their faith and ours was the ſame, though ſome more particular Articles are now revealed, which they did not ſo par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly and diſtinctly apprehend; but yet ſo as that in the general they
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:119845:67"/> agreed with us in the faith of a <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah.</hi> Some (in <hi>Lombard)</hi> are bold <note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi prius.</note> to name particulars, as <hi>Chriſts Birth, Death,</hi> and <hi>Reſurrection;</hi> and <hi>Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi prius.</note> concludeth for the neceſſity of explicit believing of his <hi>Incarnation</hi> in all times, becauſe it was the means of ſalvation; which reaſon will hold alſo for the neceſſity of belief of his <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Reſurrection.</hi> For my part, I dare not be over-confident to determine for particulars, but that in general, that all that were ſaved then and always, were ſaved by faith in a <hi>Meſſiah</hi> and <hi>Saviour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor this with ſuch an implicit faith as <hi>Lombard</hi> ſpeaks of, <hi>viz.</hi> in believing what their <hi>Majors</hi> or <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours</hi> believed, <hi>quibus fidem ſuam committebant,</hi> to whom they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted their faith, and pinned it on their ſleeve, to which purpoſe they ridiculouſly apply that in <hi>Job, Boves</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 1. 14.</note> 
               <hi>arabant, &amp; aſinae paſcebantur juxta eos,</hi> too <hi>Collier-like,</hi> or rather <hi>Aſse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like</hi> a faith for them that are made wiſe to ſalvation.</p>
            <p>Much leſs may we grant, that they knew more of <hi>Chriſt</hi> then the very <hi>Heathens</hi> did, in whom there
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:119845:68"/> was not ſo much as an <hi>implicit</hi> faith of a <hi>Saviour</hi> in any tolerable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. <note place="margin">See <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deaux, ubi prius.</hi>
               </note> At beſt were but <hi>Deiſts,</hi> (as I may ſo call them) <hi>i. e.</hi> that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their woful manner worſhipped a <hi>God</hi> without any true knowledge of a <hi>Redeemer, indeed were without God, and without hope, as well as ſtrangers from the Common-wealth of Iſrael,</hi> Coloſſ. 2. 12.</p>
            <p>Of which number <hi>Cornelius</hi> was not, as they would have him, and accordingly bring him in frequently in their writings, as an inſtance of an <hi>Heathen,</hi> who yet <hi>feared God, and and whoſe alms and prayers</hi> (and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note place="margin">Acts 10. 2. 4. <hi>Lombard, ubi prius. Auſtin de praedeſt. c. 7 Gregor. Hom. 19. in</hi> Ezek. <hi>Aquin. 3. in parte tertia, q. 69 art.</hi> 4.</note> his perſon) <hi>were accepted by God.</hi> For he was a <hi>Proſelyte,</hi> and living among the <hi>Jews,</hi> had the ſame faith of a <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> that they had. Believed that he was to come, but was at firſt ignorant that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> was he, and ſo that he was come; to certifie him whereof, <hi>Peter</hi> was by God ſent unto him. And thus much for their Plea taken from the <hi>Jews,</hi> and others before Chriſt; The laſt is from</p>
            <p>Infants,</p>
            <p>Or the children of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dying
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:119845:68"/> 
               <hi>Infants,</hi> and others that are <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted,</hi> or were <hi>deaf</hi> and <hi>blind</hi> from the womb; and ſo without this poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility of having <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſo revealed to them, as for them by faith to lay hold on him, and yet who dare ſay, that none of them have been, are, or ſhall be ſaved by him? Eſpecially the children of believing parents dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their infancy, whom the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture giveth us better hopes of. And therefore as theſe are ſaved <hi>Chriſto ſatisfaciente non recepto,</hi> ſo why might not the Heathens alſo be <hi>ſine Chriſto Chriſtiani,</hi> (as he calleth them) or if they had not Chriſt revealed to them in an extraordinary way, and faith infuſed into them, yet why <hi>might it not be by his own power and Spirit, imputing and applying the merits of a Saviour unto them, although</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>N. Calver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> of the light of Nature.</note> 
               <hi>they wanted an hand of faith to lay hold on him. For although whereſoever Chriſt is offered and diſplayed, there iudeed is neceſſarily required the mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and reciprocall act of the creature to embrace and entertain him; yet where he is not at all, or not clearly made known, even there God according to his diſtinguiſhing goodneſſe (if he
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:119845:69"/> will) can accept of ſome for his ſake, which is but a kinde of preventing and anticipating love, as all the love of God is, and in his infinite wiſdome can find out ſeveral ways of ſaving ſuch by the pleonaſme of his love in Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> So that what in an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary way may be granted to <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants,</hi> for want of age, or to <hi>diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted</hi> ones for the want of reaſon, the like may ſeem may juſtly be indulged to <hi>Heathens,</hi> invincibly ignorant of a <hi>Saviour,</hi> for want of means to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt him unto them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To which I anſwer, that indeed I find <hi>Zuinglius</hi> putting theſe together, and making their caſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, which yet is much different: For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. It cannot rationally be ſaid, that there was an equall invincibility of ignorance in thoſe <hi>Heathens,</hi> to that which is in <hi>Infants</hi> and <hi>diſtracted perſons,</hi> which want the uſe of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, which they had; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore might have made more uſe of it then they did; and therefore their ſin was more wilful, and ſo made them more obnoxious to <hi>Gods</hi> wrath, which therefore theſe <hi>Infants, &amp;c.</hi> as
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:119845:69"/> leſs guilty, may in reaſon better e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape.</p>
            <p n="2">2. How God worketh in, or deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with elect Infants, which dye in their infancy (for any thing that I have found) the <hi>Scripture</hi> ſpeaks not ſo much, or ſo evidently, as for me (or it may be for any) to make any clear or firm determination of it. But yet ſo much as that we have thence ground to believe, that they being in the Covenant, they have the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of it, <hi>Acts 3. 25. Gen.</hi> 17. 7.</p>
            <p>Whether God may not work and act faith in them then, (as he made <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> leap in the womb) which <hi>Beza,</hi> and others of our Divines de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, <note place="margin">Luke. <hi>Luther in</hi> Gal. 3. <hi>Kemnit. in Seſſ. 7. Concil. Trident.</hi>
               </note> and others are not unwilling to grant, I dare not peremptorily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine. Yet this I may ſay, that he acteth in the ſouls of Believers <hi>in articulo mortis,</hi> when ſome of them are as little able to put forth an act of reaſon, as they were <hi>in articulo nativitatis.</hi> But the Scripture (for any thing that I know) ſpeaks not of this, and therefore I forbear to ſpeak any thing of it. Only (as I ſaid) it giveth us ground to believe, that they being in the Covenant may
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:119845:70"/> be ſo wrapt up in it, as alſo to be wrapt up in the <hi>bundle of life,</hi> and did it give us but as good hopes of the <hi>Heathens</hi> (of whom it rather ſpeaks very ſadly) as it doth of ſuch <hi>Infants,</hi> I ſhould be as forward as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to perſwade my ſelf and others, that they were in a hopeful condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>For ſuch infants, ſuppoſe they have not actual faith, ſo as to exert it, yet they may have it infuſed in the habit, they are born in the <hi>Church,</hi> and in the <hi>Covenant,</hi> and what the faith of the <hi>Church,</hi> and of their <hi>believing parents</hi> may avail them, I do not now particularly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire into! The <hi>Heathens</hi> (I am ſure) came ſhort of them in theſe advantages, nor will the pity or pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the <hi>Saints,</hi> or their <hi>Tutela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Angels</hi> (to which <hi>Collius</hi> hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, as to an <hi>Anchora ſacra,</hi> for
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>De anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Pagan. lib. 2. ca.</hi> 14</note> their ſafety) ſave them from a wrack, which he thinks they may, although they did not pray to them: This difference between them, and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of believing <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that <hi>theſe</hi> by virtue of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant they are in may and ought
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:119845:70"/> to be baptized, which no <hi>Heathen</hi> till he profeſſe his faith, can lay any claim to, no more then till he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, he can to the Covenant. And if <hi>God</hi> did not vouchſafe him ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient means of ſalvation, it is a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving ſign, and ground of fear, that in his juſt Judgement, he let him fall ſhort of ſalvation, which both by his original and actual guilt he had juſtly forfeited.</p>
            <p>And whereas mention was made of an <hi>anticipating and preventing grace of God, by which without faeith he might be ſaved;</hi> I conceive and believe that it is abundant <hi>anticipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and preventing grace,</hi> when ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in <hi>Him</hi> or in <hi>any, God</hi> beginneth and worketh faith to lay hold on <hi>Chriſt.</hi> But ſuch a preventing grace as to accept us for <hi>Chriſts ſake with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out faith in Chriſt,</hi> the Scripture men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioneth not, is a new <hi>notion</hi> of a <hi>young Divine,</hi> which without bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter proof muſt not command our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, or impoſe upon our credulity.</p>
            <p>And the like I may ſay of <hi>imputing Chriſts righteouſneſse and ſatisfaction to them without their receiving of it, and him by faith.</hi> For it is that which
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:119845:71"/> the <hi>Scripture</hi> owneth not. It ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth account that it is indulgence e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to impute <hi>Chriſts</hi> merits to us, in and upon our taking hold of <hi>him</hi> by faith, which is therefore ſaid to be <hi>imputed to us for righteouſneſſe,</hi> Rom. 4, 5. 22.</p>
            <p>And whereas it was ſaid, that God <hi>could do it if he would,</hi> we do not diſpute of his <hi>extraordinary or abſolute power,</hi> and what by it he can do; but what in the diſpenſation of grace he <hi>doth,</hi> and declareth in <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture</hi> he <hi>will doe.</hi> And as for that, although <hi>he is able to doe more then we can think,</hi> yet his <hi>will</hi> muſt not <note place="margin">Eph. 3. 20</note> be meaſured by our <hi>thoughts,</hi> nor may we pitch upon ways of ſalvation of our own deviſing; for what rare contrivances here would <hi>ſelf-love</hi> and a <hi>luxuriant phanſie</hi> make? But muſt hold to what he in his word hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed, to be his own way, which in the matters, as of his <hi>worſhip,</hi> ſo of his <hi>free grace,</hi> he will have the liberty of making the choice and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of.</p>
            <p>And therefore in the laſt place, for that <hi>Pleonaſme</hi> of love, by which this way (it was ſaid) they might
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:119845:71"/> be ſaved. I, with <hi>Paul,</hi> thankfully acknowledge not only a <hi>Pleonaſme,</hi> but even an <hi>hyper-pleonaſme</hi> of love as the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> word is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 14. but I pray read on, and ſee what immediately fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth there in the very ſame ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, where it is added, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>it is in Chriſt Jeſus with faith and love;</hi> but to extend it to them (eſpecially in this way) that were wholly ſtrangers to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> never knew him, never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved in him, or loved him ſaving<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and above all, (whatever <hi>Collius</hi> weakly diſpute's to the contrary) is a <hi>Pleonaſme</hi> indeed of a ſparkling wit and pen, according to <hi>Quinti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians</hi> deſcription of a <hi>Pleonaſme. Qui</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib. 1. cap.</hi> 15, 16, 17.</note> 
               <hi>fit, quoties verbis ſupervacuis oneratur Oratio;</hi> a neat expreſſion, and a piece of a <hi>ſtrong line,</hi> but no ſolid <hi>Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> in the Text telleth us, that <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides</hi> or without <hi>Chriſt,</hi> we muſt look for no ſalvation. Which therefore</p>
            <p n="1">1. As before, ſhould teach us with an holy and awful trembling and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence to adore Gods holy counſels and righteous diſpenſations towards thoſe <hi>Heathens,</hi> which (by what
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:119845:72"/> hath been ſaid) appear to be in a very doubtful and dangerous condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which though to us may ſeem ſevere, yet take we heed of blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming them for being unjuſt, leſt <hi>God</hi> at the laſt clear his righteouſneſs in our confuſion. His Juſtice is as infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite and incomprehenſible as his Mercy; and therefore we who eaſily grant that his mercy is more then we can comprehend, ſhall then as plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be made to ſee, that his Juſtice is more then we can fathome, which yet becauſe we cannot now compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend, we too preſumptuouſly take the boldneſs to implead and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme; to be ſure <hi>God will be cleared</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 51. 4.</note> 
               <hi>when he is judged,</hi> &amp; therefore we had need take heed that we be not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned when <hi>God</hi> ſhall at laſt come to judge us, as for other matters, ſo for thoſe <hi>hard ſpeeches,</hi> which ſome
<note place="margin">Jude <hi>v.</hi> 15</note> have ſpoken againſt him, and thoſe horrid imputations which they not more frequently then boldly load his decrees and proceedings in this kinde with, which although they blaſpheme as none of his, yet ſhould they at laſt prove indeed to be ſo (as many as gracious and able as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:119845:72"/> judge they are) ſuch a queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as you read, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 19. 22. will not be then to be anſwered, or not without confuſion when God ſhall ask, <hi>Whom haſt thou reproached and blaſphemed, and againſt whom haſt thou exalted thy voice, and lifted up thine eyes on high?</hi> if with him, thy conſcience ſhall then be enforced to make that anſwer there following, <hi>even againſt the holy One of Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such I ſay, therefore had need be more wary, and forbear ſuch horrid expreſſions and imputations, leſt their preſent confidence do not hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily, or rather moſt unhappily end in confuſion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This ſhould rather teach us with all humble thankfulneſs to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire <hi>Gods</hi> diſtinguiſhing mercy to us under the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> who by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation of it hath removed thoſe difficulties which made their eſtate (at the beſt) ſo extreamly doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</p>
            <p>Hath ſo ordered that we ſhould be born and live, neither in the <hi>mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night</hi> of <hi>Heatheniſme,</hi> where no light of ſalvation by <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhined, nor in
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:119845:73"/> the <hi>twy-light of the Law,</hi> under whoſe <hi>veils</hi> this ſaving light appeared ſo obſcurely.</p>
            <p>Hath not ſuffered us to die <hi>Infants,</hi> but hath let us live till we could put forth acts of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> that ſo alſo we might act faith in a revealed <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hath not bereaved us of the uſe of of our <hi>Beaſon,</hi> as in thoſe <hi>diſtracted</hi> ones inſtanced in, or of our <hi>Senſes,</hi> as thoſe who are born deaf and blind, &amp;c. but that we may read the <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures,</hi> hear the <hi>Goſpel</hi> preached, and know the <hi>myſteries</hi> of our ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Which therefore ſhould be our ſerious care and endeavour ſo to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove theſe bleſſed helps and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages in laying hold on <hi>Chriſt</hi> by faith thus revealed, and in <hi>working out our ſalvation</hi> by him purchaſed, that as we <hi>are the children of the light, ſo we</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 5. 8 Matth. 11. 20. to 25. Heb. 2. 3.</note> 
               <hi>may walk as ſuch,</hi> leſt our condition prove far worſe then the <hi>Heathen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> whileſt we ſo manifeſtly <hi>neglect ſo great ſalvation,</hi> concealed from them, but openly manifeſted to us; for which with the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> let us hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly <note place="margin">Pſal. 147. 12.</note>
               <pb n="143" facs="tcp:119845:73"/> and heartily bleſs the <hi>Lord,</hi> and ſo let the laſt word of his <hi>Pſal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> be the laſt of this Diſcourſe. <hi>Halelu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jah.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 147. 20</note>
            </p>
            <p>Halelujah, <hi>Salvation, glory, and honour, and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rev. 19. 1. 2. Ver. 3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>power unto the Lord our God, for true and righteous are his judgements.</hi> Halelujah, <hi>Amen,</hi> Halelujah.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
